<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Catastrophe mundi, or, Merlin reviv'd in a discourse of prophecies and predictions and their remarkable accomplishment : with Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphicks exactly cut, and notes and observations thereon as also a collection of all the antient (reputed) prophecies that are extant touching the grand revolutions like to happen in these latter ages / by a learned pen.</title>
            <author>Learned pen.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32469</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12696970</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12696970</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65898</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48496)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65898)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1529:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Catastrophe mundi, or, Merlin reviv'd in a discourse of prophecies and predictions and their remarkable accomplishment : with Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphicks exactly cut, and notes and observations thereon as also a collection of all the antient (reputed) prophecies that are extant touching the grand revolutions like to happen in these latter ages / by a learned pen.</title>
                  <author>Learned pen.</author>
                  <author>Lilly, William, 1602-1681. Monarchy or no monarchy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 123 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by John How ... and Thomas Malthus ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A re-isssue of the appendix to "Monarchy or no monarchy" by William Lilly--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prophecies.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Prophecies.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Cataſtrophe Mundi:</hi> OR, <hi>MERLIN</hi> REVIV'D, In a DISCOURSE of PROPHECIES &amp; PREDICTIONS, And their Remarkable Accompliſhment.</p>
            <p>With Mr. <hi>LILLY</hi>'s <hi>Hieroglyphicks</hi> EXACTLY CUT; And Notes and Obſervations thereon.</p>
            <p>AS ALSO A COLLECTION Of all the Antient (Reputed) PROPHECIES That are Extant, Touching the Grand Revolutions like to happen in theſe <hi>Latter Ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Learned Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and are to be Sold by <hi>John How</hi> at the Seven Stars at the South weſt Corner of the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Malthus</hi> at the Sun in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT has been (Scandalouſly) reflected hy For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, That <hi>Engliſhmen alwayes car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry an old Prophecy in their Pockets</hi> (ſee Fullers <hi>Church-Hiſtory,</hi> Lib. <hi>16.</hi>) yet to do our Nation Right, we may modeſtly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ow, That we are no more Addicted to thoſe Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oſities than our <hi>Neighbours.</hi> Tis well known <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>w fond the <hi>French</hi> are of their <hi>Noſtradamus;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Prediction touching a <hi>Red-hair'd Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>te</hi> hath not wanted its Impreſſions on one of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reateſt Spirits</hi> in <hi>Europe;</hi> Nor is there ſcarce Cardinal at <hi>Rome,</hi> but is <hi>in Fee</hi> with an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rologer</hi> to advertiſe him of his Fate, and when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e luckly Hitt of the <hi>Infallible Chair</hi> will fall his ſhare. It muſt not he denyed, That many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve rendred themſelves <hi>Ridiculous</hi> in <hi>Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>g,</hi> and more been <hi>Befool'd</hi> in <hi>Crediting</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anciful or Knaviſh <hi>Prognoſticks</hi> of ſome En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uſiaſtical or <hi>Deſigning</hi> Heads; whence the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſdom of our Anceſtors has thought fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ain and chaſtize with Penalties, <hi>ſuch as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>me to publiſh falſe and Phantaſtical Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s, to the Intent thereby to make any Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>on, Inſurrection, Diſſention, loſs of life, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:65898:3"/>
Diſturbance in the Realm,</hi> Stat. <hi>5.</hi> Eliz Cap. <hi>15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſmall Treatiſe is <hi>Chaſte</hi> from any ſuch <hi>lewd Deſign,</hi> rather aiming at the direct contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; For underſtanding that certain <hi>Pictures</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Emitted by Mr. <hi>William Lilly</hi> have much been talkt of and admired, (perhaps for their being ſcarce and unknown <hi>(Omne enim Ignotum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur pro Magnifico)</hi> and that the ſame have lately been <hi>Republiſht</hi> by one, That not only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends ſo ſhrewdly to underſtand them, That he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> adventur'd to place them in a <hi>new Order,</hi> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo has added <hi>others</hi> of his own Invention, and fathers the former (though we think without any grounds) on <hi>Noſtradamus;</hi> adding likewiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>veral further <hi>odd</hi> Prognoſtications, wherein 'ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> probable <hi>preſent Confidence</hi> is all the Hope of <hi>future Verity:</hi> we conceived it could be no of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence to gratify the <hi>Curious,</hi> truly with thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Emblems,</hi> juſt as they were ſet forth by Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> now ſix and twenty years ago; Which as <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle</hi> ſaid of ſome of his works, are <hi>ſo publiſht,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> not to be publick; Becauſe I think, ſcarce Intel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligible to any, till <hi>Time</hi> (the beſt Expoſiter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Oracles</hi>) ſhall unlock the Myſtery. At leaſt, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that expect the fulfilling of them <hi>All</hi> in this o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Age, (nay, or in that of our Grand-Children) m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> find themſelves as groſly miſtaken as thoſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> were ſo confident of the final Deſtruction of <hi>Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and the Papacy in <hi>66;</hi> ſince Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:65898:3"/>
tells us, That <hi>therein is Repreſented the fu,+ture Condition of this Nation, For many hundred of years yet to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the reſt of the <hi>Prophecies</hi> (for we uſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he vulgar stile) hereunto annexed, all the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed World knows they are none of our Deviſing, but have long ſince been vouch'd by many Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Authors; And as we undertake not to Juſtify <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir <hi>Authority,</hi> ſo neither do we preſume to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir <hi>Interpretation.</hi> All we had to do, was to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecite them Faithfully,</hi> and give the Reader <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he moſt certain Account we could of their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, withal rectifying diverſe groſs miſtakes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith which (through the Negligence of <hi>Tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers,</hi> Ignorance of <hi>Tranſlators,</hi> or Errors of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſs</hi>) moſt Copies of them formerly did abound; and ſo they are left to the Cenſure of the Reader, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Poſterity, which more juſtly by the <hi>Event</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill know, what Value to put upon them.</p>
            <p>What ever ſucceſs they ſhall have, or whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orthy of <hi>Regnard</hi> or <hi>Contempt,</hi> we ſhall here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nclude with an <hi>Infallible Prophecy,</hi> that for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er concerns all the Nations of the World in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eneral, and each perſon in particular, and which we are certain ſhall come to paſs, for the Youth of <hi>Eternal Truth</hi> hath ſpoken it: —<hi>If thou ſhalt hearken diligently unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice of the Lord thy God, to obſerve and to all his Commandments, That then the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rd will ſet thee on high above all Nations of
<pb facs="tcp:65898:4"/>
the Earth. Bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the City, and Bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the Field.—The Lord ſhall cauſe thine Enemies that riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee to be ſmitten before thy face, and all that thou ſetteſt thine hand unto ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper.— But if thou wilt not hearken to the Lord thy God, to obſerve and do his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and his Statutes, Curſes ſhall come upon thee and overtake thee: The Lord ſhall ſend upon thee Vexation and Rebuke, until thou be deſtroyed: And ſhall ſmite the with Madneſs and Blindneſs, and Aſtoniſhment of Heart, and thou ſhalt grope at Noon days as the Blin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gropeth in darkneſs, and thou ſhalt not proſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, but be oppreſſed and ſpoiled, and no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall ſave thee.</hi> Deut. <hi>28.</hi>
            </p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <lg>
                  <l>Dicamus bona verba; Deus regit Aſtra; ferunt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Illius Arbitrio Sydera, Terra, fretum.</l>
                  <l>Sed Heu, quam noſtra malis deliret moribus Aeta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ipſa etiam videas Sydera moeſt a queri.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>God</hi> moves the Heavens, and his <hi>Mighty</hi> Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Both Planets, Earth, and Ocean doth Comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>But we alas! are now ſo <hi>wicked</hi> grown</l>
                  <l>That Threatning <hi>Stars</hi> our vileneſs does bemoa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>And with our weighty ſins both Heav'n an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Earth do groan.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65898:4"/>
            <head>Of Prophecies, Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Divinations in General.</head>
            <head type="sub">And many Remarkable <hi>Inſtances</hi> of <hi>Things</hi> foretold, that came to paſs.</head>
            <p>AS 'tis not our purpoſe to ſpeak of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Prophecies</hi> or thoſe <hi>Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> Contained in the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> which <hi>alone</hi> are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and of infallible Credit and Authority; ſo neither ſhall we run through all thoſe Follies and wicked Extravagancies whereby the Heathen pretended to diſcover things to come. As their <hi>Auguries, Aruſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Sortileges,</hi> &amp;c. But only to raiſe ſome few Remarks on ſome of the Celebrated <hi>Methods</hi> whereby things are thought to be predicted or foreknown, and frequently come to paſs accordingly. Of this ſort are,</p>
            <p n="1">I. That of <hi>Wiſe</hi> Prudent and Learned men, who <hi>from their Obſervations</hi> out of Hiſtory, Their knowledge of the Nature of men, and the Conſtitutions of Governments, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring times paſs'd, with the preſent, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65898:5"/>
concluding from like Cauſes, like Effects, when they ſee the ſame things come again upon the ſtage of the World, as have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been, and then conſidering all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Agreement and difference, are able to give a very <hi>probable Conjecture,</hi> which ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom fails, of what is like to come to paſs. Which ſort of Predictions are not only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but worthy of much Commendation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oftimes conducible to the good of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, by Premoniſhing and Preventing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences like to come upon them.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Aſtrological Predictions, when the Artiſt undertakes from the Poſitions of the Heavens, the Configurations of the Planets, Eclipſes, Conjunctions, Comets <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell future Accidents, or as one very ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantly defines it.—<hi>Aſtrologia eſt Doctrina quae oſtendit vires Stellarum cognitas Perpetua Experientia, et Qualitates, Temperamenta et Inclinationes in Elementis et Corporibus Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ortas a Luce, Motu, et Influentiis Stella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum; Quibus Qualitatibus, Temperamentis et Inclinationibus, Reſpondent ſuae quaedam Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, niſi aut Divinitus, aut aliis Cauſis For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioribus Impediantur.— Aſtrology is a ſort of Learning which ſhews the Force and Vertues of the Stars, known by perpetual Experience, and the Qualities, Temperaments and Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ariſing from the Light, Motion and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluencies
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65898:5"/>
of the Stars, in the Elements and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of men; Anſwerable to which Qualities Temperaments and Inclinations are their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, unleſs hindred by Divine power, or ſome other ſtronger Cauſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Art I cannot ſay is unlawful, but I take it to be but Conjectural, and by Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Pretenders much abuſed: ſtrange things have been, and frequently are thereby foretold, and prove true, when a skillful Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt hath the handling of the matter; but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times fall out otherwiſe: ſometimes from the Ignorance of him that undertakes the Judgment, otherwhile from the Influence of ſome of the <hi>fixed Stars;</hi> which being ſeldom taken notice of, may croſs or hinder what may otherwiſe be ſignifyed; Or 3dly, from the want of a ſufficient Treaſure of Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by which Judgment ought to be given; The ſame poſture of the Heavens having ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver twice hapen'd alike in every circumſtance ſince the Creation, and by that means leaving the World deſtitute of ſtable means whereon to build their Judgment; ſince what can be rationally ſaid in that kind muſt proceed from the Comparing of Events which have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened under ſuch and ſuch Configurations, with what are like to be when the ſame fall out again; Or laſtly, by reaſon of the care of the party himſelf, who may by his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65898:6"/>
prevent what from the Influence of the Stars would have been his Deſtiny, for they at moſt do not <hi>Neceſſitate,</hi> but <hi>Incline,</hi> and by the Providence and over-ruling Power of God, and the Wiſdom of Man, are ſometimes diverted.</p>
            <p n="3">III. A Third ſort is a Geomantical or Terreſtrial Divination, in which from cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain voluntary Pricks or Points made by the hand at Adventure, certain Figures are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; From the firſt four of which, called <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> are produced other four, called <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> Theſe Eight bring forth four <hi>Grand Children,</hi> from them come out Two <hi>Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> from thoſe a <hi>Judge;</hi> and the Judgment upon this ſort of Divination is not much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like that of Aſtrology. But the Foundation of all this ſeems to be laid upon a falſe Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, That the Soul of man knoweth things to come, but is hindred by the dulneſs of the Organs of the Body. And therefore in the practice of it, a great ſedateneſs of mind is required, a freedom from all noiſe that may diſturb it, and ſuch like Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; Which he that hath a mind to fool a way time, may find in <hi>Cattan, Flood,</hi> and <hi>H. de Piſis.</hi> But this kind of Divination I take to be idle, vain and ſuperſtitious, as not built upon any ſtable Foundation of Reaſon, or ſupported by any thing but Fancy.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65898:6"/>IV. A Fourth ſort is by framing certain Figures of Stone or Metal underneath ſuch Conſtellations, and placing them either in ſome Conſpicuous Place or Town, or ſometimes Under-Ground, by which ſome have pretended to do ſtrange Feats; Theſe are called <hi>Taliſmans,</hi> of which, (as alſo the Language of the Stars, with an Alphabetical Table, and how from <hi>That,</hi> words are fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med which ſhall declare the Event of things to come, according to the Nature of the Queſtion) <hi>Gaffarel,</hi> a Learned <hi>French-man,</hi> hath largly written in his Book of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nheard-of Curioſities;</hi> and ſuch no doubt they will prove to him that ſpends much time in the ſtudy of them.</p>
            <p n="5">V. A Fifth ſort (if indeed there be any ſuch thing) may be by <hi>Communication with Angels and Spirits;</hi> For many have pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſuch a Converſe; I do not mean by the <hi>Black-Art,</hi> Conjuring, <hi>Negromancy</hi> or hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to do with Devils; but with good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, who out of Charity, Love and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to their Fellow Creatures, are ſaid of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to be willing to forewarn them of impen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding dangers, and diſcover to good men what may be of advantage. Thus the Learned <hi>Brown</hi> in his <hi>Religio Medici</hi> ſticks not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his opinion to be, That Mankind owes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65898:7"/>
the Invention of many of our excellent and profitable Arts to the <hi>Courteous Revelation of Spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. Laſtly, There is <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> or Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, an Enlightning of the whole Soul, either from a certain unuſual <hi>Craſis,</hi> or an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-poize of Complexion, or ſtrength of purer Spirits, or elſe by ſome unknown ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural means, as the Poſſeſſion or Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſome Spirit, either good or bad. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tells of one <hi>Maracus</hi> of <hi>Siracuſe,</hi> a Poet, who never made ſo good Verſes as when he was mad; and immediately before that Story hath theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. <hi>Many becauſe that Heat is near the ſeat of the mind, are taken with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Frantick and Enthuſiaſtick Fits, from whence they become Sybills, Bachides, or inſpired, not from any Diſeaſe, but a Natural Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> —So that it ſeems in the ſenſe, of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> much of this kind of Illumination proceeds from an Exaltation of the mind by ſome <hi>Ecſtatick</hi> operation of the Soul; and great Examples in all Ages, might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced out of the Obſervations of Phyſitians to this purpoſe; ſome whereof have been meer Cheats to gain Credit to ſuch as ſhould Cure or Exorciſe them; Others <hi>true</hi> and <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural,</hi> where ſome Melancholy Heat, or ſtrong <hi>Imagination,</hi> or laſtly, through <hi>Cuſtom</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65898:7"/>
uſe, the perſons affected have brought upon themſelves ſuch an Habit, that fancy prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over their Judgment and Underſtanding, they have pretended to Propheſy; and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times what they have ſpoken, hath proved true.</p>
            <p>Of theſe ſeveral ſorts of foretelling, as touching the Aſtrological Predictions, or ſuch as are gtounded on that Art, we have briefly ſhewn whence they may pretend to Credit, having in themſelves a natural ground, as Effects are foreſeen in their Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. But as touching the Common Abſtruſe Indications of great Accidents, Wars, death of particular men, Caſualties to Cities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> uſually ſtiled <hi>Prophecies,</hi> from what ſpring to derive them, or to what Cauſe they ought to be attributed, is difficult to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>To deny that any things have been ſo fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, or that becauſe ſome pretending there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, were either <hi>Cheats,</hi> or <hi>Hypochondraique,</hi> That therefore all were ſo, is to give the Lie to the experiences of all Ages, and in many of them the very great time between the Predictions, and the fulfilling of them, doth ſufficiently Evince that they came from an higher Cauſe than a Melancholy Heat: For where that is predominant, I have ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that between the Propheſie, and the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65898:8"/>
time alotted for the Accompliſhment, there is rarely or never more than a ſcore of years, ſometimes not ſo many Moneths.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Concerning the <hi>Sybils,</hi> not only the Heathen paid a great veneration to their Verſes, but the moſt Eminent Antient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Chriſtian Church have made great and good uſe of them (in that kind of way which <hi>Logicians</hi> call <hi>Argumentum ad hominem</hi>) to Convince their Pagan oppoſers of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our Religion, ſince they gave ſo clear a Teſtimony to the Birth and other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> long before his Incarnation. But whether all or any of them were indued with the Holy Spirit of God, I dare not affirm. This difference I obſerve to be between them and the true Prophets, that the later were never during their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy deprived of their Witts, Senſes or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; For if at any time they have been ſurpriſed with Conſternation or Aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment upon the Appearance of an <hi>Angel,</hi> or the like, they have been by the Power of God ſoon reſtored to a Temper fit to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and deliver the Meſſage wherewith they were Intruſted. Nay they have generally been further able to Confirm by a Miracle, that they were really ſent from God, when it ſtood with his Glory to have it ſo, and the diſtruſt of the people required it; whereas
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65898:8"/>
theſe <hi>Sybils</hi> are never reputed to have done any other Miracle, ſave that of truly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling things to come. 'Tis indeed in the 18th of <hi>Deutrenomy,</hi> made the Mark of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>not ſent</hi> by God, if the things foretold <hi>come not to paſs,</hi> and this is undoubtedly true. But it follows not <hi>Convertibly,</hi> that whatever things foretold come to paſs, the perſon foretelling them muſt needs be ſent by God; except meant <hi>permiſſively;</hi> For we know the Oracles of the Heathen Idols, gave often true Anſwers, ſuffered ſo to do indeed by God, but inſpired by the Devil. And <hi>Balaam</hi> though he were a Magitan and wicked perſon, yet he foretold ſeveral excellent Truths.</p>
            <p>I am not Ignorant, That many times, as appears from Hiſtory, falſe Prophecies and Predictions have been promoted by crafty Knaves to deceive credulous Fools, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their own Deſigns, and many that have vainly truſted in them, have been deceived and brought to Deſtruction by their over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fondneſs. At ſuch time as <hi>Brittanicus</hi> wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the great Lot of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, by the Encouragement of a vain Aſtrologer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e loſt both Hopes and Life by the Rigour of a Bloody Tyrant. <hi>Seneca</hi> by a pretty fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, brings in <hi>Mercury</hi> perſwading with the Gods that they would abridge the Life of <hi>Claudius,</hi> if not for any other Cauſe, yet out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65898:9"/>
of very Pity and Compaſſion to the poor A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers, who had already been taken with ſo many Lies about it. That <hi>Wily Fox, Traja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> (as <hi>Dion</hi> tells us) by the practiſe and Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Aſtrologers convey'd a pannick fear into the Head of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> That <hi>Germanicus</hi> aſpired to the Empire, whereas in the mean time he only puſht forwards his own Deſign: <hi>Exiſtimans ſe cum Juvenem ſuſtuliſſet, Facile in Manu Senem Habiturum;</hi> Concluding it would be eaſy to get the old man into his Clutches, if he could but get rid of the Young One. So <hi>Richard Duke</hi> of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> finding that ſo long as his Brother <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Clarence</hi> ſtood between him and the <hi>Gole,</hi> he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver win the <hi>Prize</hi> on which he had fixt his Ambitious Thoughts, cauſed a certain Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy to be ſuggeſted to the King his elder Brother, That <hi>G.</hi> ſhould one day wear the Crown. During the Civil Wars between <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey,</hi> neither party wanted Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, which both gave them Encouragement to Proceed, and hope to prevail. And in like manner in our Domeſtick Broiles between <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> The Books of Beaſts and Babies were exceeding rife and currant in every Corner of the Realm, either Party Applying and Interpreting as they were Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the Title. <hi>Don John de Barbuda,</hi> a Nobleman of <hi>Caſtilé,</hi> of greater Courage
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65898:9"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han Judgment, being perſwaded by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of an old ſilly <hi>Hermite,</hi> that without the loſs of one mans Life, he ſhould recover the Kingdom of <hi>Granada</hi> from the <hi>Moors,</hi> undertook the Enterpriſe againſt the Advice and Perſwaſions of the King of <hi>Castile,</hi> with no greater force than 1000 Foot and 300 horſe, who were together with himſelf all Cut in pieces.</p>
            <p>Remarkable is that Story of <hi>Baſſianus Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacala,</hi> who during his War in <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> ordered one of his Counſellors at <hi>Rome</hi> call'd <hi>Maternianus</hi> to procure a Meeting of all the Prophets, Aſtrologers and Conjurers, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover if any Plot or Deſigns were in hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his perſon or Authority; and <hi>Mater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianus</hi> finding by their Univerſal Verdict that one <hi>Macrinus</hi> a Colonel, who had a charge in the Field at that very inſtant, under rhe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, ſhould bereave him of his Life, ſent Advertiſement thereof by the next diſpatch; which Poſt happening to arrive at a time when the Emperour was exceeding earneſt and attentive at his Sport, he commanded this very <hi>Macrinus,</hi> who (as Fate would have it) was next at hand, to break up the Pacquet and inform him of the contents at the time of Councel. By this means <hi>Macrinus</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the drift and his own danger (though before never no thought of Diſloyalty, much
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65898:10"/>
leſs murder of his Prince, came into his head) finding there was no middle Courſe to be taken, but that either <hi>Caracalla,</hi> before he ſhould receive further Advertiſement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or to be ſure he himſelf ſoon after, muſt dye for it, made Choice of a deſperate Ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian that Commanded a Company of foot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, To <hi>Stabb</hi> his Maſter, as he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew from Company to Eaſe Nature; and ſo ſtrangely ſolv'd the Credit of the South-Sayers.</p>
            <p>In the time whilſt Popery and Monkery bore ſway in <hi>England,</hi> There was a great <hi>Loobily Image</hi> in <hi>Wales</hi> called <hi>Darvel Gathern,</hi> of which an old Prophecy went, <hi>That it ſhould burn a Forreſt,</hi> and on that Account was beheld by the Ignorant with much Venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But the Event was thus: At the time of the Diſſolution of Abbeys under <hi>K. Hen.</hi> 8 it was brought up to <hi>London,</hi> and burnt at the Gallows in <hi>Smithfield</hi> with the Bowels of one Friar <hi>Forreſt,</hi> executed for a Traitor.</p>
            <p>Another Prophecy was current in the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey of <hi>Glaſſenbury,</hi> That <hi>a Whiting ſhould Swim on the Topp of the Torr thereof,</hi> (which is a ſteep Hill hard by,) and the Credulous Countrey People underſtood it of an Inrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sea, which they ſuſpected accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly. But it hapen'd, that Abbot <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> the laſt of that Character at <hi>Glaſſenbury,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65898:10"/>
was hanged thereon for his Recuſancy to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render the Abbey and denying the Kings Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, ſo ſwimming in Air and not Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and waved with the wind in the place, made good the Prophecy, though very unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly.</p>
            <p>Did not <hi>Anaximander</hi> of old foretell the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> of a dangerous and greivous Earth-quake imminent, adviſing to prevent the Peril and Terror thereof by forſaking their Houſes and avoiding the City, to remain till its fury was over in the open Field<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? which Earth-quake ſhortly after burſt out in ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent manner That the whole City was utterly ruinated, and a great part of the Mountain <hi>Tagetus</hi> horribly overwhelm'd? did not the Prince of Phyſitians, <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> forſee a dreadful plague, or mortal Contagion amongſt the <hi>Greeks,</hi> a conſiderable time before it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to rage? Did not <hi>Thales Mileſius</hi> inrich himſelf by foreſeeing a Scarcity of Olives in the <hi>Mileſian</hi> Fields, and buying up a great quantity before hand? Did not <hi>Socrates</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell the death of <hi>Crito? Sulla</hi> the Death of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligula?</hi> The <hi>Caldeans</hi> the Death and Parri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide of <hi>Aggripina</hi> the Empreſs by her own Son <hi>Nero,</hi> when he ſhould come to be Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour? and yet ſo poſſeſs'd ſhe was with the Devil of Ambition, that ſhe cry'd out <hi>Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat modo Imperet — I ſay with all my Heart,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65898:11"/>
Let him kill mee, provided he may but Raign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great was foretold his Fate by <hi>Calanits</hi> and <hi>Indian,</hi> and that if he Entred <hi>Babylon</hi> it would prove fatal, and he would dye there; which came to paſs accordingly. <hi>Caeſar</hi> had fair notice given him by <hi>Spurina</hi> to beware of the <hi>Ides</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> and fell a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to his own Incredulity or Negligence, in not obſerving that Caution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſcletarion</hi> the Mathematician, being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed that he had predicted the Death of the Emperour <hi>Domitian;</hi> The Emperor demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of him whether he had ſo done, or not? And confeſſing that he had, <hi>Then</hi> (quoth the Emperor) <hi>Pray Sir, you that are ſo Skillful in finding out other Peoples Fate, tell me what ſhall be your own:</hi> To which he anſwered, <hi>That he ſhould very ſhortly be torn to pieces by Doggs. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minitian</hi> reſolves (as he thought) utterly to ſpoil this Prediction, and therefore having order'd him forthwith to be put to Death, Cauſes his body to be laid in a very deep ditch and a great heap of Earth to be laid thereon, that no Dogs ſhould come near it; But migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Rains happening, waſht away the new un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled Earth, and Dogs did accordingly tear his Body; And ſoon after <hi>Domitian</hi>'s Death confirmed the reſidue of his Prediction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rantzovivus</hi> a Noble and Learned <hi>Dame,</hi> p.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65898:11"/>
99. tells us, That the Aſtrologer of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Frederiek</hi> the Second, being queſtion'd by him, why he paid ſo much reſpect to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphus</hi> Earl of <hi>Haſpurgh,</hi> than but a poor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer to the Court, Anſwered; <hi>Becauſe all thy Sons being Dead,</hi> (and the Emperour at that time had no fewer than 10 alive) <hi>He and his Poſterity ſhall come to and Enjoy thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes whieh now your Majeſty does poſſeſs;</hi> Which was anſwered with a punctual Succeſs, <hi>Rodolphus</hi> being Elected King of the <hi>Romans</hi> by the <hi>Germans, Anno</hi> 1273. And page 97. he Relates, That one Maſter <hi>Chriſtian</hi> an Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger of <hi>Prague,</hi> Admoniſhed <hi>Ladiſlaus Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gello</hi> King of <hi>Poland</hi> by a Prieſt that belonged to him, <hi>Anno</hi> 1434. That he ſhould beware of Death that year, for that many Planets were then Conjoin'd, and there would be an Ecclipſe of the Moon under the Earth, and accordingly the ſame year he was Lodg'd in his Grave.</p>
            <p>In the ſame page, he gives that Remarkable Inſtance of the Incomparably Learned <hi>Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Picus Mirandula,</hi> having written and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a very ſmart Treatiſe againſt Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, ſeveral Artiſts, <hi>viz. Bellantius</hi> of <hi>Sena, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius Sirigatus</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi> and <hi>Angelus de Cataſtiris</hi> a <hi>Carmelite,</hi> That they might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the Truth of their Art and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him of his Miſtake, poſitively told him
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65898:12"/>
in their publick Writings, That he himſelf ſhould not Eſcape or Survive the 33d year of his Age, by reaſon of the Direction of the Aſcendant in his Nativity to the Body of <hi>Mars;</hi> who flattering himſelf with a falſe Conceit, As if he could wrangle away Death, or elude the Significations of his Stars by Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> indeavouring to prove the Art vain, his Death concurring exactly which the Time predicted, Confirmed the ſame Art to be true, and more actually Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed all that he had written againſt it, Than if all the World beſides had Conſpired to Anſwer him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fulgoſius, Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Ca.</hi> 11. Records the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous exploits perform'd by <hi>Guido Bonatus</hi> the Aſtrologer at <hi>Forly</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> at what time that City was cloſe Beſiedg'd; For he Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or fortold a Lucky Day, for <hi>Guido</hi> Earl of <hi>Montferrat,</hi> wherein if he would make a Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſhould rout his Enemies and obtain over them a Compleat Victory, but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out receiving a <hi>ſlight wound in the Knee.</hi> And that the Earl might be more aſſured of what he ſo foretold, <hi>Bonatus</hi> would needs march out along with him, and carryed Towe and Eggs and other Neceſſaries for dreſſing his wound. And in the Engagement the Enemy was vanquiſht, and the Earl wounded punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the place foretold.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:65898:12"/>
               <hi>Regiomontanus,</hi> a little before his death at <hi>Rome,</hi> viz. in the year 1475. (One hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Thirteen yares before it came) pointed out the year 1588. as a time of moſt ſignal Revolutions and grand Tranſactions in the world. And to the ſame purpoſe there was a Prophecy publiſht in High Dutch, as followeth.</p>
            <q xml:lang="dut">
               <l>Tanſen funfhundert achtzitchtacht</l>
               <l>Das iſt das iar, das ich betracht</l>
               <l>Geth in dem de weltnixt under</l>
               <l>Geſchicht doth groz merklich wunder.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Which I have found thus paraphras'd into <hi>Latine.</hi>
            </p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <l>Poſt mille expletos a partu Virginis Annos</l>
               <l>Et poſt Quingentos rurſus ab Orbe datos</l>
               <l>Octogeſimus Octavus mirabilis Annus</l>
               <l>Ingruet, is ſecum triſtia Fata feret</l>
               <l>Si non hoc Anno, totus malus occidet Orbis</l>
               <l>Si non in Nihilum terra, fretumque ruet:</l>
               <l>Cuncta tamen mundi Surſum ibunt atque retrorſum</l>
               <l>Imperia: &amp; Luctus undique grandis erit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And may bee thus Engliſh.</p>
            <q>
               <l>From Chriſto Birth count a Thouſand Years compleat,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:65898:13"/>And add five hundred more with Eighty Eight</l>
               <l>That year approaching, all men will affright</l>
               <l>With wofull Terrors, which on them will light</l>
               <l>If the whole world to ruin do not run,</l>
               <l>Or into nothing Land and Seas bee done:</l>
               <l>At leaſt moſt Realms ſhall Topſy Turvy turn,</l>
               <l>And men on all ſides Lamentably mourn.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now if wee examine our Chronicles, wee ſhall find moſt memorable paſſages in diverſe parts of the world to have happend in that year. Was it not unuſual and ſtrange, That <hi>Poland</hi> this year ſhould have three Kings aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Title, whilſt the Fourth, viz. <hi>Stephen Battori</hi> was yet unburied? Namely, <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> the <hi>Swede, Maximilian</hi> the Emperors Brother, and <hi>Henry Valois</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> Of which three, <hi>Maximiliam</hi> in the begining of this year was taken priſoner, his Army Cut in pieces, and by means there of many thouſands of men women and Children carryed away Captives by the <hi>Tartars.</hi> That <hi>Suedeland</hi> in the mean tyme was all in a Combuſtion which Tumults, and loſt ſeverall ſtrong Places to the <hi>Muſcovite.</hi> The <hi>Muſcovite</hi> himſelf ran madd, and loſt his witts. The King of <hi>Denmark Frederick</hi> the Second dyed. In <hi>France</hi> there happend The <hi>Barricado</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> The flight of the King from thence, The ſlaughter of the great Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:65898:13"/>
and his brother the Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain:</hi> The Death of the Queen Mother, The poiſoning of the Prince of <hi>Condee,</hi> and the Overthrow which the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> gave unto Duke <hi>Mercoeurs;</hi> All which gave that Kingdome ſufficient Cauſe to think 88. a year Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary. At the ſame tyme the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy</hi> prepared his Army and ſurprized the French Kings cheif Magazine in <hi>Saluze.</hi> The <hi>Sophy</hi> of <hi>Perſia</hi> dyed, The <hi>Turks</hi> ſuffered great Defeats in <hi>Hungary.</hi> And in <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople</hi> by reaſon of falſe moneys paid to the <hi>Janizaries,</hi> they fell into a Mutiny, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd the Grand Seignior to deliver up his cheifeſt Favourites to bee put to Death, ſet fire on the Jews Houſes, and ſpoiled their goods, by which means above 12 thouſand Houſes were burnt down to the Ground in that City.</p>
            <p>And nearer home, did not the world with wonder behold the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armado (which they fooliſhly called <hi>Invincible</hi>) ſhatter'd to pieces by the valour, of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> A loſs that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monarchy has not recovered to this day. In a word, (ſaith <hi>Gallo Belgicus) Ortu ſolis uſque ad occaſum, nullus ferme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſit locus in quo non miratu dignum aliquid hoc Anno contigerit. From the riſing of the Sun to the going down thereof, there was ſcarce any place, in which ſomething wonderful did not happen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:65898:14"/>'Tis a very odd Story, which is credibly related of King <hi>James,</hi> how he was premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht of his death by a Dream, wherein his old Maſter <hi>Buchanan</hi> appeared unto him in his ſleep, and gave him theſe two Verſes:
<q xml:lang="lat">
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sexte verere Deum tibi vitae Terminus inſtat</l>
                     <l>Cum tua cadenti flagrat Carbunculus igne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sixth <hi>James!</hi> ſee thou to God do humbly turn</l>
                     <l>Thy Fate draws near, and men thy death ſhall mourn</l>
                     <l>When in the Fire thy Carbuncle ſhall Burn.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> was the ſixth of that name of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and next morning he told his Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber-men and ſeveral of the Lords, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating the verſes, and averring that he did not make them. The ſucceſs was this: The King had a very large and fair Carbuncle Stone uſually ſet in his Hat, and ſitting by the Fire not long after, this great Carbuncle fell off into the Fire, and a <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Lord took it up, and 'twas obſerved the King ſickened and dyed very ſhortly after.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with that moſt poſitive prediction of <hi>Michael Noſtradamus</hi> of St. <hi>Remy</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> Phyſitian to the King, and a great Mathematician and Aſtrologer, who dyed the ſecond of <hi>July</hi> 1566. In his Book
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65898:14"/>
of <hi>Quadrins</hi> in <hi>French,</hi> Printed 1555. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he very plainly foretells the horrid and deteſtable Murther of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt by his own Subjects before his own Palace. And in <hi>Quadrin</hi> 51. thus evidently fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaks the Burning of <hi>London,</hi> and expreſſes the very year 66. in theſe words.</p>
            <q xml:lang="fre">
               <l>Le Langue du Juſte a Londres fera faut</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bruſlez</hi> par Foudres, de <hi>vingt trois, les ſix</hi>
               </l>
               <l>La Dame Antique cherra de place haut</l>
               <l>De meſme Seicle pluſieurs ſerront <hi>Occis.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Which may thus be Engliſht.</p>
            <q>
               <l>For th' Blood o'th Just a London ſpilt, the ſame</l>
               <l>In Sixty Six ſhall all be in a Flame;</l>
               <l>That Antient Dame ſhall in the Duſt complain</l>
               <l>And many of the ſame Sect ſhall be ſlain.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But we are affraid we have already wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Reader with theſe <hi>paſt Stories;</hi> and therefore now proceed to gratify ſuch whoſe Curioſity delights in ſuch matters, with Mr. <hi>Lillies Hieroglyphicks</hi> as they were by him publiſht 1651. with (only) this following <hi>Preface.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:65898:15"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Lillies</hi> Account of his <hi>Hieroglyphicks.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAd the Courteſie of the preſent times de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it at my hands, thou hadſt ſeen an Explanation of the following Pages, which in <hi>Aenigmatical</hi> Types, Forms, Figures, Shapes, doth perfectly repreſent the future Condition of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation for many hundred of years yet to come. I have borrowed ſo much time from my Morning-ſleep as hath brought forth theſe Conceptions. You that Read theſe Lines muſt know I do no new thing: I do herein but imitate the Antients, who ſo often as they reſolved to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal their Intentions from prophane Hands, uſed <hi>Hieroglyphicks, Images,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Egyptian</hi> Prieſts were herein excellent, and their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment commendable: Our Saviour alſo himſelf commendeth; <hi>Ne detur ſacrum Canibus.</hi> If Providence ſhall hereafter aſſign me a quiet life, and prolong my years, I may then perhaps leave unto the Sons of Art the ſeveral Changes of every Kingdom and Commonwealth in <hi>Europe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> in ſuch-like Characters as theſe which now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65898:15"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:16"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:65898:16"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:17"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:65898:17"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:18"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:65898:18"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:19"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:65898:19"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:20"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65898:20"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:21"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:65898:21"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:22"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:65898:22"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:23"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:65898:23"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:24"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:65898:24"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:25"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:65898:25"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:26"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:65898:26"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:27"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:65898:27"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:28"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:65898:28"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:29"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:65898:29"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:30"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:65898:30"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:31"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:65898:31"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mr. Lilly's hieroglyphic (symbolic prophecy)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:65898:32"/>
            <div type="commentary">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:65898:32"/>
               <head>Notes or Obſervations on the foregoing Figures, and the Nature of <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphicks</hi> in General.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EGypt</hi> (the fruitful <hi>Parent</hi> of ſo many <hi>Miracles</hi>) has alwayes boaſted her ſelf one of the moſt <hi>Early Nurſes</hi> of <hi>Learning:</hi> The <hi>Grecians</hi> in the Days of <hi>Solon, Pythagoras, Herodotus</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> Travel'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hither for the Knowledge of Nature, and the Acquiſition of thoſe <hi>Sciences,</hi> which rendred them ſo famous. But the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Prieſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto whom it belonged to teach, did never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivulge their Doctrines without a <hi>Shadow,</hi> or ſome dark Repreſentation ſufficient and very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pt in it ſelf to denote the matter they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, many times more ſignificantly than many words could do, yet not ſo obvious to be underſtood by the vulgar; whereby they I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined they kept their <hi>Myſteries</hi> from Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nation: Eſpecially thoſe which related to <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eir <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> were wrapt up in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain viſible Shapes and Forms of Creatures, thoſe Inclinations and Diſpoſitions did lead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the knowledge of the Truths, intended or Inſtruction; and they by a peculiar name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere called <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> derived from the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65898:33"/>
Two Greek words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Sacred;</hi> an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>Ingrave;</hi> as much as to ſay, a <hi>Holy Inſcription,</hi> or Sacred <hi>Engravement.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe all their Divinity, Philoſophy, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> choiceſt Secrets, were comprehended in theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ingenious <hi>Characters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor were they only Contriv'd to hinder the ſublime knowledge of Philoſophy fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> being profaned; But alſo that they mig<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Abbreviate</hi> the diffuſed Notions of that Sci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence, and fit them for a more eaſy Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and better Retention in their Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Every Name is an Abreviation of a Thing, but it is not able to give ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Idea of the Properties and hidden Qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lities of the things intimated, as the <hi>Picture</hi> of them in a witty <hi>Hieroglyphick.</hi> And further the Egyptians by theſe Inventions had a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſign to render their Knowledge <hi>Immortal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> for which purpoſe they did Ingrave them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Obelisks</hi> and Pillars of Marble, and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> long before the uſe of <hi>Paper,</hi> (an Invention originally too of the ſame Country, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed at firſt of the Flakes of certain Sedgie Reeds growing on the Banks of the <hi>Nilt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> called <hi>Papyri,</hi> moiſtned with the glutinou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> water of the River, then preſs'd together and afterwards <hi>dry'd</hi> in the Sun) as is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident from thoſe Verſes of the lofty <hi>Luc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>can.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:65898:33"/>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ondum flumineos</hi> Memphis <hi>contexere Libros, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>overat, in Saxis tantum Volucreſque fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeque,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulptaque Servabunt Magicas Animalia Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emphis <hi>yet knew not how with Reeds to frame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or Books, but Birds and Beaſts Letters became, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd Animals Engrav'd on laſting ſtone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith Magick Tongues, Learning preſerv'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor did they only expreſs particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngs and ſome Secret Knowledge by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eir <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> but alſo <hi>whole Sentences,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riting all their Rules and Precepts rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g to the Worſhip of their Gods, or to the <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>vernment of the Kingdom in this manner; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich will not appear ſtrange or incredible ſuch as have Convers'd in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> to tis known that there to this day, there three or four Nations whoſe Languages as remote and different as <hi>Hebrew</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ek,</hi> or <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>Welch,</hi> who yet under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd one anothers Writings. So that what <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> writes in one Language, the other can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d their own, which could not be but by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> or Univerſal Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s (an Art commendably attempted of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:65898:34"/>
late amongſt us, by the Reverend and Lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed <hi>Wilkins,</hi> in his Book on that Subject) R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſenting the ſhapes of things, which a known to men of all Nations and Tong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> A writing of which Nature was ſent to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Learned <hi>Bochartus</hi> from an Eminent per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> for him to Inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pret.</p>
               <p>But to give the Reader a Taſte of this ki<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Egyptian Myſtery, Take theſe few <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
               <p>They Repreſented the <hi>Providence of</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by a <hi>Baſilisk,</hi> with an Hawks Head and Ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> becauſe there is no other Creatures fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Spirits and Vigour, or more quick-ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>The Power of God they did expreſs by <hi>Body and three Heads,</hi> (by which one wo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> almoſt have thought they had ſome notice the Trinity) but <hi>without either Hands Feet;</hi> becauſe Almighty God governs things only by his Wiſdom and good ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, and needs no viſible Members to p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duce his wonders.</p>
               <p>To ſignify the Effects of Gods power Nature, they painted a man with a Mul<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude of <hi>Hands,</hi> ſtretching them out upon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> World.</p>
               <p>The <hi>World</hi> was ſometimes repreſented a <hi>round Temple,</hi> becauſe Divine Majeſty ha<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:65898:34"/>
Created it for his own Glory, to receive therein the Adoration and Homage of all Creatures; becauſe it appears like a large and Beautiful Edifice, excellently well adorned, ſupported by Gods Power, Covered with the Heavens, and diſtinguiſht into ſeveral Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But its Ordinary <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> was <hi>a Globe,</hi> in which were drawn the Circles of the Zodiack, with the Signs in it, and round about a Multitude of Stars. This Globe was ſupported on the back of a man upon his knees, which were Cover'd with his long Garment, to ſhew how the World is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by Gods Providence, which ſeems to be Cover'd to the lower Ranks of Creatures with divers Emblems and dark Shadows.</p>
               <p>When they intended to point out the continual Mutation of Creatures, and the Change of one Being into another in the World, they uſed to put <hi>a Snake</hi> repreſenting <hi>an Orb,</hi> biting and devouring its Tail, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the World feeds upon its ſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives from its ſelf a continual ſupply of thoſe things that Time Conſumes. The ſame was alſo an Embleme of <hi>the Year,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth run round; and where the Old Year ends, the New one begins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> was painted as a Beautiful Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with four Ears and four Hands, but
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65898:35"/>
with <hi>one</hi> Tongue, which was <hi>hid</hi> within her Lips, that were ſhut Cloſe.</p>
               <p>Unity was repreſented by the <hi>Sun</hi> and its Beautiful Beams; Peace and Worldly Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by the fruitful <hi>Olive-Tree;</hi> Liberty and Pleaſure by the <hi>Vine;</hi> Chaſtity by Beams; and a Plentiful Encreaſe, by <hi>Muſtard-Seed,</hi> which grows up into many and large Branches.</p>
               <p>The Relation between Heaven and Earth was ſignifyed by a man, with hands tyed with <hi>a Chain,</hi> that was let down from the Clouds, for there is nothing here below either ſo great or powerful but it is held by a Secret Chain, by which the Divine Providence can turn and wind it at pleaſure.</p>
               <p>A furious man, was intimated by a <hi>Lyon</hi> eating up his Prey; A Religious man by a Lion running from a <hi>Cock.</hi> A <hi>Whore</hi> by a Lion with a Womans head, becauſe her Countenance is fair, her Speech moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and her Allurements powerful, but her Nature fierce and cruel, and ſhe intends only to prey upon both Body and Eſtate. A Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful man, was painted having Compaſſion on a Lamb lying at his Feet.</p>
               <p>A cunning Selfiſh Time-ſerver was expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by an <hi>Hedg-hog,</hi> becauſe this Creature wraps himſelf up in his own <hi>Warm Down,</hi> and turns out <hi>Prickles</hi> to all the World beſides; and alſo becauſe it hath alwayes two or three
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65898:35"/>
holes where it retreats, and when the wind is cold and boiſterous at one hole, it creeps to the <hi>other,</hi> and thus it changeth its dwelling with the Weather.</p>
               <p>A man proud of his Natural or acquired Abilities, was ſignified by a <hi>Peacock</hi> with beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Plumes, in a poſture of admiring them, and expoſing them to the Sun-Beams.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Graſhopper</hi> was the <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> of an <hi>Egyptian Prieſt</hi> learned in the Myſteries of Heaven: For as the Graſhopper deſerv'd their Admiration, becauſe it ſings ſo well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Tongue; ſo theſe men that attained to ſuch excellent perfections as the knowledge of God and the Superiour Beings, by dark <hi>Hieroglyphicks</hi> and ſignificant Shadows, did no leſs require their Wonder and Eſteem.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Chameleon</hi> denoted an <hi>Hypocrite</hi> that ſtudies to pleaſe the times in which he lives, and that can be of any Religion, and take any Impreſſion that will ſerve his preſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orn; for it is reported of this Animal that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t can change it ſelf into any colour but White and Red.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Prophet,</hi> or <hi>Prophecy</hi> was expreſſed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mole,</hi> a Creature that is without eyes, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew that man is naturally blind, and can have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o clear foreſight of the time to come, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t a Divine Revelation, and then the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate Events of the future, do appear unto
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65898:36"/>
us with many doubts and dark ſhadows, which hinder us from a perfect and clear Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Revenge,</hi> was intimated by a <hi>Tyger</hi> devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Horſe; a good Eye-ſight, by a Lynx, which is a Beaſt near of Kin to a Wolf.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Lampray</hi> with an Eel was the Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphick of <hi>Adulterers,</hi> for the <hi>Lampray</hi> is a Fiſh that ſeeks the Company of other Fiſhes of the ſame ſhape, for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſome ſay that they are venemous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they joyn themſelves with Snakes and other Water-Serpents.</p>
               <p>The Head of a man ſignifies ſound Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Wiſdom: His Hair cut off, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Grief or Bondage; If growing, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. The Forehead is the ſeat of Pride and Impudence. The Eye wide open, the token of Wiſdom and Juſtice, the ſeat of Contempt, the Throne of Love, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer of other paſſions of the Soul. The Noſe being large, a Mark of quickneſs of Apprehenſion, and the Excellency of our Underſtanding. The Mouth was the <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphick</hi> of Modeſty; The Heart of Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Shoulders, of Strength; The waſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hands, of Innocency; The Right-hand, of Power, Fidelity, and Favour. The Knee expreſs Humility and Compaſſion; The Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Freedom; a Crown, Dignity; a Scepter
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:65898:36"/>
Power; a Buckler, Defence; an Arrow, Speed; a Spear, War or Valour; a pair of Ballances, Equity; a Sword, Revenge or Cruelty; A ſitting poſture intimates Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; an Anſwer, Hope; The Palm and Laurel, Emblems of Victory and Honour; The Myrtle, of Pleaſure; The Cedar, of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity; The Oak, of Strength; the Olive, of Fruitfulneſs; the Lilly, of Beauty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to come nearer our preſent ſubject— 'Tis not infrequent in the Holy Scriptures to expreſs Perſons, Kingdoms, Judgments, and other things to come, after this manner, <hi>Hieroglyphically,</hi> by the names of Beaſts, Birds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Judah</hi> was propheſied of, by the name of a Lion: <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> of an Aſs: <hi>Dan,</hi> of a Serpent: <hi>Napthali,</hi> of an Hind: and <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> of a Wolf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. from the 3d to the 28th verſe. And the Babylonian Monarchy, both Heatheniſh and Myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> was Propheſied of by the name of an <hi>Eagle,</hi> by ſeveral of the Prophets, as <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.40. and 49. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Obad.</hi> 4. and <hi>Hab.</hi> 1. and <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras</hi> did Propheſie of it by that name, about 300 years before ever the Eagle was portray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Roman Enſigns, and became the Badge or Arms of that Empire. Which was firſt given by <hi>Marius,</hi> becauſe being a Child, he found an Eagles Neſt and ſeven young ones therein; whereupon in his ſecond Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65898:37"/>
going againſt the <hi>Cinbri</hi> (the Antient Inhabitants of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Hoſtein</hi>) he cauſed an Eagle to be pictured in his Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard; Which was afterwards peculiarly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by the Roman Legions, to ſhew that they would with as great Courage fall upon and engage the Enemy, as the Eagle on his Prey.</p>
               <p>The Holy Books of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyps, or Revelations of St. <hi>John</hi> the Divine, do alſo afford us ſeveral Inſtances of <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies,</hi> Kingdoms, and Calamities, repreſented by ſeveral Beaſts, Vials, Seals Trumpets.</p>
               <p>We mention not theſe Sacred Authors, as intending to compare or Rank theſe <hi>Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyphicks</hi> here before ſet down in the ſeveral Figures, with thoſe Divine Prophecies: far be it from us to advance any ſuch bold and irreverent Blaſphemies; we recite them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew, that the ſhadowing out of future Events in ſuch a way, and under ſuch myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Figures, is no novel or upſtart Inven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, but has long been uſed in the world.</p>
               <p>As to theſe preſent <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> we call them Mr. <hi>Lillies,</hi> becauſe by him they were firſt made publick in the year 1651. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by him originally deviſed, we cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine; for as I remember, Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf about 10 years ago, told me, he borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and was not the firſt Inventer, but
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65898:37"/>
ſaid he knew the right Key or Signification of them, and that he doubted not but Poſterity, when Fate ſhould think fit to diſcloſe its My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Book, and reduce the matters thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be prefigured, into Act, would be well aſſured of their Verity. But that they are, or ever were, or ought to be accoun<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Hieroglyphicks</hi> of <hi>Noſtradamus,</hi> I ſaid no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority or proof, though it had pleas'd a late Author ſo to call them.</p>
               <p>Nor ſhall I undertake to decip<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> or pretend to acquaint the world with the meaning thereof or when each particular is to be fullfilled. The Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>London</hi> ſeems very plainly to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> been one of thoſe Accidents here inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and indeed there are two figures that may ſeem to have reſpect hereunto; but I am apt to believe one of them, <hi>viz.</hi> that where the <hi>Twins (Londons</hi> Celeſtial Aſcendent, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Aſtrologers) are tumbling down headlong into the Flames, ought to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood Metaphorically, as of Heats and Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities induſtriouſly ſpread amongſt her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nhabitants by ill men, to put them into a <hi>Combuſtion,</hi> and this I am the rather inclined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o judge, obſerving two Perſons pictured powring in <hi>Jars of Oyl</hi> to encreaſe the Flames.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:65898:38"/>As touching the <hi>Moles</hi> which you will find in many of the Figures very buſy; the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinion is, that they ſignifie the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> Popiſh Prieſts, and other Emiſſaries of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> aptly Emblem'd by the <hi>Mole,</hi> as being carryed on with a <hi>blind</hi> Zeal, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging their miſcheivous Intrigues under-Ground, in Maſquerade, and without owning publickly their helliſh Deſigns.</p>
               <p>I have heard, that Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> the more to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure the Signification, Tranſpos'd ſeveral of the Figures, and did not ſet them in that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>place,</hi> as they were to fall out in reſpect of <hi>Time.</hi> However we thought fit, punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to obſerve his Copy: And ſo thou haſt them juſt as he firſt publiſht them, without Addition, Diminution, or Alteration.</p>
               <p>In the next place, we ſhall ſubjoin ſeveral antient Predictions, which ſo long have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the name of PROPHECIES, that they may now ſeem to plead Preſcription for that Title; Which be pleaſs'd to take as follows.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <div type="prophecy">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:65898:38"/>
               <head>The Prophecy of Rabbi <hi>Elias,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the End of the World.</head>
               <p>THe words in the Original, as they are deliver'd in the Talmudical Books, and and particularly in the Treatiſe or Section intituled <hi>Havoda Zara,</hi> Cap. 1. are theſe in Hebrew:</p>
               <q xml:lang="heb">  
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tana abe Elihau ſeſeth Alaphim ſana have Haolam: Sene Alaphim Tohu: Vſne Alaphim Thora: Vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Alaphim Iemoth hamas ſihi uba Havenothema Serabu Iaſhu meon Maſcias.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>In Engliſh thus, <hi>verbatim.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>  
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thus ſaid the Sons (or Diſciples) of</hi> Elias: <hi>The World conſiſteth of Six Thouſand Years; Two Thouſand years Void, Two Thouſand the Law, Two Thouſand the Meſſias: But for our ſins, which are many, thoſe years of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber are over-paſſed, which are over-paſſed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>Whether by this <hi>Elias</hi> they would have us underſtand the <hi>Divine Tiſhbite</hi> of that Name, who after ſo many Miracles, recorded in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65898:39"/>
Scripture, done on Earth, was taken up viſibly into Heaven; or whether they intend by it ſome <hi>Latter Rabbin,</hi> may be queſtion'd, but I the rather think the laſt: Though 'tis certain this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> or if you pleaſe <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> or <hi>Diviſion</hi> of the Continuance and ſeveral Ages of the World, has been all along of great eſteem not only amongſt the Jews, but alſo with the moſt Learned and Famous Doctors of the Chriſtian Church; For both <hi>Lactantius, Hierom, Hillary, Ambroſe,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> of the Antient Fathers, and alſo <hi>Melancthon, Peucer, Poſtellus, Reſlyn,</hi> and many other Modern Learned Men, mention it with reſpect.</p>
               <p>The meaning of the firſt part of the words ſeem very plain, That the <hi>Duration</hi> of the World ſhall be the Term of Six Thouſand years, which ſhould be divided into three Grand, Intervals, Spaces, Periods, <hi>viz.</hi> Two Thouſand years from the Creation to the giving of the <hi>Law,</hi> (which ſpace of time is here called <hi>Tohu, void,</hi> becauſe the World was then without the written Law, and without the External Ceremonies, which were afterwards Enjoin'd.) Two Thouſand years more, under the Law; and the other Two Thouſand under the <hi>Meſſias.</hi> Not that this is to be underſtood <hi>exactly</hi> to a year, in each, but 2000, a round Number,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65898:39"/>
is uſed for the Number punctual and Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; and indeed agrees very well with the Truth of Chronology; For from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the time of the Inſtitution of Circumciſion, (from whence we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly enough Date the time of the Law, though not fully delivered till diverſe years after) there were 2047 years, as may be made appear from Scripture-Calculation. And from thence to our Saviours Incarnation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 19 hundred years, or very near 2000. But ſince this Prophecy is Jewiſh, and in ſo high an Eſteem with that Nation, and does ſo clearly point out the coming of the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> to be about the year of the World 4000, and that 'tis notorious, the ſame is ſo many ages ſince paſt, it may be wondred, why even from hence they ſhould not be Convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced both that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> is long ſince come, and that our Lord Chriſt muſt needs be He. But ſuch is the obſtinate Blindneſs of that People, that they reſolve to perſiſt in their Error and Infidelity, and will rather invent any Evaſions than acknowledge the Evident Truth, as appears in this very Caſe, and will help us to fiſh out the meaning of thoſe laſt words of this Prophecy—<hi>But for our Sins, which are many, the years of that Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber are over-paſs'd which are over-paſs'd.</hi> Which words ſeem to be added to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:65898:40"/>
it ſelf, by ſome latter Rabbins; for you muſt note, That the <hi>Hieruſalem</hi>-Talmud being compoſed above 200 years after Chriſt, and the <hi>Babylonian</hi>-Talmud 400 years after Chriſt, in both which this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy is mentioned, The Authors thereof, finding the Term limited already expired, added this Clauſe to ſolve the buſineſs, and perſwade their People that the reaſon why the Meſſias was not yet come according to this Prediction, was the Multitude of their Sins which retarded his appearance, and this they give out to be the Cauſe thereof to this day. Note that <hi>Talmud</hi> ſignifies as much as <hi>Doctrinale, The Book of Doctrine;</hi> and the Books ſo called, do contain, <hi>Traditions</hi> and <hi>Obſervations,</hi> which they pretend to have been delivered by God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> beſides the Law written, and from him to have been brought down from hand to hand amongſt the Rabbins, juſt as the Papiſts ſet up their Traditions as of equal Authority with the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Agreeable to this Cabbaliſtical Prophecy or Tradition, ſome Learned men, ſuppoſing that by the ſix days of Creation, mentioned in the firſt of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> The whole Age of the World containing 6000 years, was Myſtically and Allegorically ſhadowed out, To be Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted or Deciphered in ſuch ſort, that the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:65898:40"/>
firſt days work ſhould import or prefigure a certain Reſemblance or Type of ſuch fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture matters and Events, as were perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the firſt Thouſand years of the World; The ſecond days work of ſuch as ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently happen in the Second Thouſand years, and ſo forth of the reſidue, even to the Accompliſhment of 6000 years, At which period the Eternal Requies, or Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of the Lord ſhould finally enſue, and gloriouſly appear; even as after ſix days Work God ſtayed or reſted at the firſt, and as now our weekly Sabbath (which is a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend figure of that great Everlaſting Sabbath) doth after every 6 days ſucceſſively approach. Purſuant, I ſay, hereunto, they have diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſeveral Millenaries, as in this Table.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Days.</cell>
                        <cell>Millenaries.</cell>
                        <cell>Years.</cell>
                        <cell>Governours of each Millenary</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Monday.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>1.</cell>
                        <cell>1000.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>ADAM,</hi> who died in the Year 930.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Tueſday.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>2.</cell>
                        <cell>2000.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>NOAH,</hi> who died in the Year 2005.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Wenſday.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>3.</cell>
                        <cell>3000.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>DAVID,</hi> who died in the Year 2929.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Thurſday.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                        <cell>4000.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>CHRIST,</hi> who was Born <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 3962.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Friday.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>5.</cell>
                        <cell>5000.</cell>
                        <cell>The <hi>POPE,</hi> who in this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod grew to his height, if we may extend it unto <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> who came to the Chair about 1074.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Saturday.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>6.</cell>
                        <cell>6000.</cell>
                        <cell>The <hi>MARTYRS,</hi> Millions having ſuffeted by Antic.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sunday.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>7.</cell>
                        <cell>7000.</cell>
                        <cell>ETERNITY.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:65898:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:65898:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:65898:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:65898:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:65898:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:65898:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:65898:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:65898:44"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:65898:45"/>If therefore this Rabbinical Reckoning be to be regarded, let us ſee about what Year of the World we are in at this preſent, and how much may be wanting of this Sum To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal 6000.</p>
               <p>The Birth of our Lord Chriſt, is placed
<list>
                     <item>By <hi>Chryteaeus</hi> In the Year of the World—3962.</item>
                     <item>By <hi>Mich. Butherus</hi> In the Year of the World—3962.</item>
                     <item>By <hi>Reniholdus</hi> In the Year of the World—3962.</item>
                     <item>By <hi>Schubertus</hi> In the Year of the World—3962.</item>
                     <item>By &amp; <hi>Cunmannus</hi> In the Year of the World—3962.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>By <hi>Funccius</hi> In the Year of the World 3963</item>
                     <item>By <hi>Luther</hi> In the Year of the World 3960</item>
                     <item>By <hi>Beroaldus</hi> In the Year of the World 3928</item>
                     <item>By <hi>Mereator</hi> In the Year of the World 3966</item>
                     <item>By <hi>Bucholzer</hi> In the Year of the World 3970</item>
                     <item>By <hi>Bibliander</hi> In the Year of the World 3979</item>
                     <item>By Card. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> In the Year of the World 3984</item>
                  </list>
So that there is not above 22 years difference amongſt them all, except <hi>Beroaldus:</hi> Let us therefore ſuppoſe it to be with <hi>Beucholzer, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Mundi</hi> 3970, adding thereunto 1683, makes 5653 years from the Creation; ſo that according to this Compute, there ſhould remain but 347 years to the final Conflagra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>viz.</hi> in the year of our Lord 2030.— But—<hi>That day and hour knoweth no man.</hi> And <hi>For the Elects ſake thoſe days ſhall be ſhortned.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:65898:45"/>
               <p>To this we think it not improper to add, That Prophecy or remarkable Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the End of the World, ſome Thouſands of years ſince delivered in Greek Acroſtick Verſes, the Initial Letters making up theſe words, <hi>JESUS CHRIST, SON OF GOD THE SAVIOUR,</hi> delivered by <hi>Sibylla E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rythrea,</hi> and recited by St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> in the 4th Book, and 23d. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Treatiſe <hi>de Civitate Dei,</hi> which I ſhall give you in the words of Him who many years ſince Tranſlated that excellent Book into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as followeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>J</hi>n Sign of Doomſday the whole Earth ſhall ſweat,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E</hi>ver to Reign a King in Heavenly Seat</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>S</hi>hall come to judge all Fleſh: The Faithful and</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>U</hi>nfaithful too before this God ſhall ſtand.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>C</hi>orporal ſhall he ſit, and thence extend</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>H</hi>is Doom in Souls, The Earth ſhall quite lye waſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>R</hi>uin'd, oregrown with Thorns, and men ſhall caſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi>dols away, and Treaſure; Searching Fire</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>S</hi>hall burn the ground, and rage with fatal Ire</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>T</hi>hrough Seas and Skyes, and break Hells blackeſt Gate;</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:65898:46"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>S</hi>o ſhall free Light Salute the Bleſſed State</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O</hi>f Saints; The Guilty laſting Flames ſhall burn;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>N</hi>o Act ſo hid but thence to Light ſhall turn;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>N</hi>or breaſt ſo cloſe, but God ſhall open wide;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E</hi>ach where ſhall Cries be heard, and noiſe betide</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O</hi>f gnaſhing Teeth, The Sun ſhall from the Sky</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>F</hi>ly forth, and Stars no more move orderly.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>G</hi>reat Heav'n ſhall be diſſolv'd; The Moon depriv'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O</hi>f all her Light: places at Height arriv'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>D</hi>epreſs'd, and Vallies mounted to their Seat,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>T</hi>here ſhall be Nought to Mortals High or great</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>H</hi>ills ſhall be Level'd with the Plains; The Sea</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E</hi>ndure no Burthen; and the Earth as They</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>S</hi>hall periſh, cleft with Lightning, every ſpring</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi>nd River burn: The fatal Trump ſhall bring</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>V</hi>nto the world from Heav'n a diſmal Blaſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi>ncluding plagues to come for ill deeds paſt.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O</hi>ld Chaos through the Scatter'd Maſs appears</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>U</hi>nto this Barr all Kings come Priſoners</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>R</hi>ivers of flaming Brimſtone drown their Tears.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:65898:46"/>
               <head>The Learned <hi>ALSTEDIUS,</hi> his <hi>SPECULUM MUNDI,</hi> and CHRONOLIGY of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Numbers.</head>
               <p n="1">1. God alone hath reſerv'd to himſelf the exact knowledge of future Things; as the incommunicable Prerogative of his Divine Majeſty: Therefore, 'tis impoſſible any man though never ſo clear-ſighted, ſhould compile an accurate Chronology for Time to come, or define the punctual Moments of Futurity; yet is not therefore the Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Prophetick Numbers to be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for ſince God hath expreſſed certain Numbers in the Hiſtories and Prophecies of his Word, it would be too great both Sloth and Ingratitude not to weigh, and with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and the fear of the Lor, denquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In obſerving the great Conjunctions or Revolutions of the Planets, as Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and over-ſcrupulous Diligence is not to be approved, ſo neither is Negligence or Contempt thereof to be allow'd.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:65898:47"/>3. The Twelfth Chapter of <hi>Daniel</hi> ought to be our Pole-Star in explaining Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Numbers, for there we are led, as by the hand, from the building of the ſecond Temple, to its Deſtruction: And from the Deſtruction thereof, which was <hi>Anno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi> 69. by a term of Days he numbers firſt 1290, and then 1335; that is in all (with the 69 years which were elaps'd from Chriſt's Birth, to the overthrow of the Temple) 2694 years: From which if we deduct the 1000 years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.2. we ſhall be brought to the year of our Lord 1694. whence we may gather, that the ſeven Vials are to be poured forth at or before that time, or their ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications to continue no longer.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The moſt eminent Mutations from the year 1600 to 1700, may be gathered from the Planetary Conjuctions, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the Apocalyptical Numbers, which point out the years—1622, 1625, 1636, 1642, 1683, and 1694.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Comparing of Hiſtories one with another, the obſervation of the Stars, and a diligent Inſpection into the manners of men, do much conduce towards our predicting of the Cataſtrophe's of humane things.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:65898:47"/>6. Thoſe Philoſophers that are more skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Aſtronomy, reckon four Monarchies, not according to the Prevalency of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, but according to the four Coaſts of the World. The firſt was of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> being the <hi>Aſſyrians:</hi> The ſecond <hi>Southern,</hi> that of the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Greeks:</hi> The third <hi>Weſtern,</hi> of the <hi>Romans:</hi> The fourth of the <hi>North,</hi> which God ſhall ſhortly ſet up in the Norrhern-parts by the Lion of the <hi>North,</hi> to the great Amazement of thoſe who ſlight the <hi>Divine Apocalypſe,</hi> and that Harmony which here we are pointing at.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The 1000 years mentioned in the Twentieth Chapter of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> ſhall begin about the year 1694, and end 2694; during which time <hi>Satan</hi> ſhall be bound, but afterward being let looſe for a ſmall time, he ſhall ſtir up <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> that is, the profeſſed Enemies of the Church, againſt the Saints; But ſhall be ſuddenly overcome, and then our Lord Chriſt ſhall come in Glory to put an end to this World.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:65898:48"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Annus Mundi Mirabilis;</hi> Or, A Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the laſt Ages of the World: Aenigmatically delivered in <hi>12</hi> Months, repreſenting ſo many notable Periods, or Cataſtrophe's, which ſhall certainly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen in thoſe times. Publiſht many Years ago, by <hi>LILLY.</hi>
               </head>
               <q>
                  <list>
                     <label>JAN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARY.</label>
                     <item>A ſhower of Blood ſhall rain continually for one hours ſpace, in a certain Land of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope;</hi> That Region, or the People thereof, ſhall firſt come to deſtruction.</item>
                     <label>FEBR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARY.</label>
                     <item>All Nations troubled with rumours of Wars, every Region preparing Armies, and Muſtering Men, Traffique generally prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited or obſtructed, by Land and Sea, each Country being inforced to live of their own ſtock and commodities.</item>
                     <label>MARCH.</label>
                     <item>The main Sea ſhall hugely ſwell with mighty Tempeſts and Winds, ſo that the Banks being overthrown, the Waves ſhall in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:65898:48"/>
many places overflow their accuſtom'd bounds, and cauſe Univerſal Innundations. One <hi>Iſland</hi> ſhall be quite overflown with the Sea, where the double Croſs hath Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſins of the Prince or Rulers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being ſo extream high againſt the Majeſty of God.</item>
                     <label>APRIL.</label>
                     <item>A terrible Sea-fight, ſuch as hath not been before, occaſioning the water to look more red than the Red Sea, the water all turned to Blood. <hi>England!</hi> thou wilt have a ſhare in this Fight, God of his great goodneſs make thee victorious; After a hard Fight thou ſhalt overcome.</item>
                     <label>MAY.</label>
                     <item>Warr and Bloodſhed over all the Earth: A certain Nation ſhall ſend ſo many Men to the Warrs, that it ſhall for a time be even deſolate of Men, ſo that twelve Women ſhall be glad of one Man: Nay, hardly procure one Young-man for them all.</item>
                     <label>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NE.</label>
                     <item>In the Eaſtern parts of the World, a whole
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:65898:49"/>
Nation ſhall Fight a great Battel in a wrong cauſe, and defend an Evil Man; but the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God will rain down a ſhower of Fire from the Throne of Heaven, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that Army wholly with all their Wealth and Treaſures, even as they lie in their Tents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <label>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LY.</label>
                     <item>So great a drought, ſo great a want of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will appear, that multitudes of People ſhall dye in many places for meer want of water, Souldiers ſhall not be able for heat to carry their Arms; The Earth ſhall be ſo dry and ſo parched with the Suns hot beams, that it ſhall yield no fruit to feed Cattle.</item>
                     <label>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST.</label>
                     <item>Great Plagues and Mortality will cover the whole Face of the Earth, and ſo deſtroy Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that there will not be ſufficient Labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to get in Harveſt, or the Fruits of the Earth. In this Month ſuch ſwarms of noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Fowls and Flies ſhall come from the Eaſt, as they ſhall devour the Corn on the Ground, the Fruit on Trees, that all ſhall be barren: Men living in thoſe times and in
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:65898:49"/>
this Month, ſhall have more ſorrow, and more woes, and more famine, and diſtreſs, than was in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when <hi>Titus</hi> beſieged it.</item>
                     <label>SEPTEMBER.</label>
                     <item>The ſeaſon of this Month will be ſo unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and the Earth ſo unfit for Tillage, that all manner of Cattle will rot on the ground, which will breed ſuch ſtore of Flies and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, that the Earth will be empoyſoned, and receive no fruit to encreaſe.</item>
                     <label>OCTOBER.</label>
                     <item>A great Famine and Dearth of Corn will over-ſpread moſt Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo that the Child ſhall ſtarve at the Mothers Breaſts, the Mother having no food to nouriſh her ſelf or Child.</item>
                     <label>NOVEMBER.</label>
                     <item>One appears ſuddenly and unexpectedly a great Conquerour, the World filled with the Fame of this Man, who ſuddenly like <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> gives Peace unto the whole Earth.</item>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:65898:50"/>
                     <label>DECEMBER.</label>
                     <item>All Warrs end, Religion truely Preached Univerſally over the World, a General Peace, no more Treaſon or Rebellion. Not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Trumpet Sounds, and Chriſt appears.</item>
                  </list>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>An Antient Prophecy of <hi>Sybella Tibur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina,</hi> found in the Year 1520. in the Bowels of the Mountain <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> after a great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation of waters which broke down part of that Mountain, and left diſcovered in the Ruins, the following words, fairly Engraven upon a large Marble Stone, in very Old <hi>Latin Characters</hi> and <hi>Stile,</hi> as follows:</head>
               <q xml:lang="lat">  
                  <p>ORietour ſydous in <hi>Europa</hi> ſoupra <hi>Iberos,</hi> ad magnam ſeptentrionis Domum; cojus Radij orbem terrarum ex improviſo illouſtrabunt.</p>
                  <p>Hoc vero erit tempore deſideratiſſimo, quo Mortalis poſitis Armeis pacem Onanimeis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectantor. Certabitor quidem varieis per diou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourni Interregni occaſionem ſtudies, cui Imperii habenae tradantor. Sed vincet tandem aviti ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinas
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:65898:50"/>
propago, quae eouſque Armorumvi progre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dietor, donec fata contraria fatis obſtiterint. Nam eodem fere tempore hoc demorſo Sydere, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum quoddam ejous Loumen longe ardentioribus mavortis ignibous exardeſcens, Antepodum fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus occludet Imperium.</p>
                  <p>At prius houic Soumittet cervices <hi>Gallia.</hi> Ad ejous genoua Soupplex adnatabit claſſibus <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tannia; Italia</hi> egre ad ardua Sceptra reſpirans, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lli languentem portendet dexteram. Verum bocce joubar ante diem ingenti mortalium deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio ſe divum non bibous condet.</p>
                  <p>Quo extincto, poſt deiras &amp; ſanguinolentas, Cometas, ignivomaſque caeli facies, nihil ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous toutum, Saloutareue erit, Oſque animanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bous coeli Firmamentum pugnantibuſque plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieis, &amp; contrarieis corſibous labefactabitor; concurrent orbibous orbeis, Fixae curſu antever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent erratitas, aequabunt aequora montes; Hec omnia denique erunt Nox, Interitus, Rouina, Dampnatio, ac ceternai Tenebrai.</p>
               </q>
               <p>In <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Thus:</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">  
                  <p>A Star ſhall ariſe in <hi>Europe</hi> over the <hi>Iberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> towards the great Houſe of the North, whoſe Beams ſhall unexpectedly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the whole World.</p>
                  <p>This ſhall be in a moſt deſired time, when
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65898:51"/>
Mortals wearied with Wars ſhall Unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly deſire Peace. They ſhall ſtrive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by occaſion of a Long-laſting <hi>Interreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> with various ſtudies which ſhall obtain the Reignes of Empire. But at laſt, the Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of the Antient Blood ſhall overcome, and proceed victoriouſly by force of Arms, until reſiſted by contrary Fates. For about the ſame time, this Star being ſet, another Coeval Light blazing with more Ardent Flames of War, ſhall ſpread his Empire even to the Coaſts of the <hi>Antipodes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But firſt, <hi>France</hi> ſhall ſubmit her Neck to his Yoak, and <hi>Brittany</hi> ſuppliant in Ships, ſhall caſt her ſelf at his Feet; <hi>Italy</hi> faintly breathing towards Scepters ſo high, ſhall ſtretch out to him her Languiſhing Hand. But this bright Beam before his time, ſhall, with the vaſt deſire of men abſcond himſelf in the Clouds of the Gods.</p>
                  <p>Who being extinct, after direful and bloody Comets, and flaſhings of Fire ſeen in the Heavens, there ſhall remain nothing for the future ſafe or healthy amongſt Men: The Firmament of Heaven ſhall be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the Planets be oppoſed in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courſes, the Sphears ſhall juſtle one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt another, and the fixed Stars move faſter than the Planets; The Seas ſwell as high as the Mountains, and nothing remain
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:65898:51"/>
but Night, Deſtruction, Ruine, Damnation, and Eternal Miſery.</p>
               </q>
               <p>This antient Prophecy is recited by <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Gemma,</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi>Supernatural Apparitions,</hi> and taken notice of by ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good Authors; As particularly by the Imcomparably-Learned <hi>Tycho Brahe,</hi> in his diſcourſe on the New Star that appeared <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1572. who thus expreſſes his Judgment of it.—There were (ſaith he) divers Expoſitions of this Prophecy, at the time when it was firſt found out, ſome interpreting it of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, others drew the meaning of it to <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and ſome thought the King of <hi>France</hi> was meant thereby; but I think that it doth rather point out thoſe <hi>Iberi,</hi> who inhabit Northward toward <hi>Muſcovia.</hi> So that this Oracle of <hi>Sybilla Tiburtina,</hi> did not denote the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> but thoſe <hi>Iberians,</hi> which are near unto the <hi>Muſcovites;</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when ſhe uſeth theſe words, <hi>Supra Iberos ad Magnam Septentrionis Domum;</hi> Over the <hi>Iberi</hi> towards the great Houſe of the North. And truely <hi>Muſcovia, Scythia,</hi> and <hi>Tartaria,</hi> do make a great part of <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo that it may well be called the great Houſe of the North; And therefore, ſince this unuſual Star did caſt is Perpendicular Beams and Influences on the Country of <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> it is not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:65898:52"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:65898:52"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:65898:53"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:65898:53"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:65898:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:65898:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:65898:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:65898:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:65898:56"/>
but that this Star, together with that Tract of Land, doth agree with the <hi>Sybilline</hi> Oracle.</p>
               <p>Thus that Noble <hi>Dane,</hi> a Perſon ſo Famous, that our King <hi>James</hi> at his Being in <hi>Denmark,</hi> went to his Caſtle of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>raniberg,</hi> to viſit him, and made theſe <hi>Verſes</hi> in his <hi>Commendation.</hi>
               </p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Quod temere eſt auſus <hi>Phaeton,</hi> vel praeſtat Apollo</l>
                  <l>qui regit Ignivomus Aethere anhelus equos:</l>
                  <l>Plus <hi>Tycho,</hi> cuncta Aſtra regis, tibi cedit Apollo,</l>
                  <l>Charus &amp; <hi>Uraniae</hi> es Hoſpes, Alumnus, Amor.</l>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JACOB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S REX.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>What <hi>Phaeton</hi> dar'd, or what's by <hi>Phaebus</hi> done,</l>
                  <l>to Rule the Fiery Horſes of the Sun?</l>
                  <l>More <hi>Tycho</hi> doth, he Rules the Stars above;</l>
                  <l>and is <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania</hi>'s Favourite and Love.</l>
               </q>
               <p>This ſame <hi>Tycho</hi> in the Treatiſe before ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hath alſo ſome Expreſſions, which we may call Prophetick; As having ſpoken of a Glorious and Happy Age to be in the end portended by that Star, and having ſtarted an Objection, that ſome might ſay, <hi>That the Light of the Goſpel and Purity of Religion, doth now ſhine out clearly, having already overcome the darkneſs of (Papal) Error.</hi> He ſhapes an Anſwer thereunto, in theſe words,—</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>If it were ſo, whence then are thoſe Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and varieties of Opinions defended by
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:65898:56"/>
Learned Men, inſomuch that the War of Pens, is more dangerous than that of Swords? Truly (ſaith he) it is rather to be feared, leſt we take this Dawning and Break of Day, to be the clear Noon-light. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I ſuppoſe that this Star doth ſignifie, that there ſhall be a new change, both in Religion, and the Eſtate of Humane Affairs; of which we may ſay,—<hi>Ventum ad ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum eſt, patiuntur ſumma Ruinam; Qui Deus in Coelis regit, &amp; reget omnia Terris.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We are come now to the higheſt perfection, the power of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhall decay, and be brought to ruin; And God who ruleth in Heaven, ſhall alſo rule all things on Earth.</p>
                  <p>But if any do object, That the end of the World is at hand, and that therefore there will not be ſufficient time to bring about a new change. I Anſwer, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth aſſure us, That the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall again be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafted into the Church before the final Conſummation of the World, which (by Humane Conjecture) muſt needs require ſome time before, they being ſcattered over the whole Face of the Earth, ſhall be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered into one Nation. And impoſſible it is, to limit and ſet forth a certain time for the Conſummation of the World, which only dependeth upon the good will and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:65898:57"/>
pleaſure of God, and is not revealed to the Angels: and therefore, cannot be known by any Humane Preſcience.</p>
                  <p>But if ſome do ſuppoſe, that the Tract of Land to which this Star was Vertical, is Ominous above the reſt, as if from thence the occaſion and Author of ſo great Muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are to be expected, we muſt then chuſe out thoſe parts of the Earth, which had the New Star in their Meridian at the time of the New Moon, next following; which fell out (accounting the time by our Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian) upon the 15th. of <hi>November,</hi> 7 hour 13 minutes, <hi>poſt meridiem.</hi> To which, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> we apply the Latitude or diſtance from the Equinoctial agreeable to the declination o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Star, which was in 61¾ the place on the Earth anſwerable thereunto, muſt needs be <hi>Ruſſia</hi> or <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> eſpecially that part there of, which is joyned unto <hi>Finland;</hi> For i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that Tract of Earth, this New Star in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> New Moon following, was in their <hi>Zenith</hi> juſt over their Heads, where it ſtood equal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly diſtant from the <hi>Horrizon,</hi> and with Right-Angled Aſpect, beheld this Country Therefore, if this Poſition of the Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> do point out the place of the Earth, from whence theſe events ſhall ariſe, <hi>Muſcov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſeems eſpecially to be deſign'd, before an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> other Regions, which are ſcituated toward
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65898:57"/>
the North, to whom this New Star was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day Vertical; whether therefore, the firſt occaſions of ſo great diſturbances and mutations ſhall ariſe from hence, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſhall be ſowed and diſperſed into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of the World, I leave to be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily decided by others. But verily, that <hi>Gogus,</hi> whereof mention is made in the 38 Chap. of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and to whom <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Ca. 17.56. and Chap. 5. doth allude, and with whom <hi>Magog</hi> is named in the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> Ca. 20. may be rightly underſtood of the <hi>Muſcovite,</hi> as <hi>Caſtellio</hi> hath interpreted it on the 38 and 39 of <hi>Ezekiel;</hi> That <hi>Gog</hi> ſhould be the Leader of the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> and <hi>Iberians,</hi> becauſe the Old Tranſlation reads it, That he ſhould be the Prince of <hi>Moſoch</hi> and <hi>Thubal,</hi> for ſeeing the <hi>Hebrews</hi> read it <hi>Meſech,</hi> and the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters do read it <hi>Moſoch,</hi> it is probable that the <hi>Muſcovites</hi> are ſignified hereby, or elſe by this name, the whole Northern Tract of Land is included.</p>
                  <p>So that 'tis very likely, that <hi>Muſcovia</hi> is Principally denoted by this Star, and <hi>Gogus</hi> their Leader, of whom it is foretold by the Sacred Prophets, and the <hi>Revelation,</hi> That having made great ſlaughter in <hi>Europe,</hi> he, at laſt with his whole Army ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, and ſo the Earth disburthen'd of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:65898:58"/>
her wicked Inhabitants; For it is probable, That there muſt be a great cleanſing and extirpation of all Earthly Impurities, before that peaceable and happy Age (whereof the Prophets have ſpoken) ſhall happen.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Thus far the words of that Great and Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Aſtronomer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>The Propheſie of <hi>Paul Grebnar</hi> of <hi>Sne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh</hi> in <hi>Miſnia,</hi> delivered by him with other things in <hi>Manuſcript,</hi> to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in the Year 1582. Obtained from her by Dr. <hi>Nevil,</hi> Clerk of the Cloſet, and preſented to <hi>Trinity College</hi> Library, where to this day it remains. This being an Atteſted Copy out of that Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal.</head>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <p>ROmano Sceptro &amp; diademate ab <hi>Auſtria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> Domo Fatali Neceſſitate depoſito &amp; ablato, eaque a <hi>Germanis</hi> &amp; exteris <hi>Gallis, Anglis, Danis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Suecis,</hi> hinc inde confluenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus oppreſſa, horribilis inde cruenta ac aterrima pugna exorietur, qua <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſa <hi>Europa</hi> graviſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me concuſſa contremiſcet, &amp; varie dilaterata, &amp; vaſtata inſignibus mutationibus obnoxia erit.</p>
                  <p>Ad eam pugnam &amp; ad faciendas Irruptiones in <hi>Pomeranorum, Megapolenſium,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:65898:58"/>
Provincias hujus temporis Rex <hi>Sueciae</hi> invitabitur, Scriptis atrocium <hi>Romanae</hi> ſedis Legatorum, quibus ſi ille obtemparaverit, ſocius belli ſed male &amp; inauſpicate fit, ipſi propinquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te conjunctiſſimus. Quamobrem <hi>Suadeo</hi> Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam in eo ſtatu quo eam acceperit, relinquat; Sic ipſe, ſtirps, &amp; poſteri ejus tranquille pace &amp; quiete fruentur, ſuis contenti quibus imperant ditionibus, gentem &amp; ſubditos ſuos reſervabunt, &amp; ſibi divinctos in Officio retinebunt. Si vero ſecum corde ſuo conſtituet populum ſuum perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, ac in devia abducere, Dominus eum e me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio tollet. Et ſic e <hi>Carolo</hi> Magnus, <hi>Carolus</hi> Regnans fit, qui Magno Succeſſu &amp; Fortuna, Septentrionalibus Populis dominabitur. Et fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciter Claſſe ſua contra <hi>Hiſpanicam</hi> potentiam &amp; Tyrannidem, ac eorum Claſſem ſeu Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ut Hoſtis pugnabit. Et una cum Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis junctibus viribus fortiter &amp; acriter dimica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit; Deus autem Regis conjugem poſitam ex hac vita evocat, unde pontifex <hi>Romanus</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num concipit, terrorem, qui poſtea Magis in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſcet cum <hi>Carolus Rex</hi> ipſe <hi>Antichriſto</hi> ſeſe opponit, eique adverſatur, Et <hi>Germanorum</hi> ac Vicinorum manui &amp; Robori ſuas copias conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, &amp; oppugnat <hi>Hiſpanicum Diadema.</hi> Et tunc <hi>Suecus</hi> feleciſſimo Succeſſu, Claſſe &amp; ſuo Populo terra marique in Hostem utitur.</p>
               </q>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:65898:59"/>
               <p>The <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>A Fatal Neceſſity having taken or torn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the Houſe <hi>Auſtria,</hi> The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Scepter</hi> and <hi>Diadem,</hi> and after an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the ſame <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Houſe, as well by the <hi>Germans,</hi> as by Forraigners, <hi>French, Engliſh, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Sweeds,</hi> making their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions on every ſide; there ſhall ariſe an horrid bloody and ſharp Conteſt, wherewith all <hi>Europe</hi> ſhall ſhake and tremble, and being ſeveral ways divided, torn in pieces, and laid waſte, ſhall be Obnoxious to many Signal Mutations.</p>
                  <p>A <hi>Sweediſh</hi> King then Reigning, ſhall, by the Writings of the Wicked Emiſſaries of the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> be invited and ſtirred up to that quarrel, and to break in upon <hi>Pomerane, Mechlenburg,</hi> and ſome Provinces belonging to <hi>Denmarke;</hi> Whereunto if he harken, he unſeaſonably and very unfortunately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes involv'd as an <hi>Allie</hi> or <hi>Confederate</hi> in a War with one that is very nearly related to him. And therefore, I adviſe him to leave <hi>Sweeden</hi> in the ſame State he found it; So ſhall He, and his Family, and Poſterity, in peace and quietneſs enjoy thoſe Dominions, over which contented they Reign, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in good Order the Kingdom, and retain
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:65898:59"/>
his Subjects devoted to his Intereſts in due Obedience. But if he ſhall imagin in his mind to pervert his People, and lead them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide out of the way, the Lord ſhall cut him off by Death. And then <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Charles,</hi> or from a <hi>Charles,</hi> a great <hi>Charles</hi> comes to Raign; who with great Succeſs and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, ſhall govern the Northern parts of the World. And ſhall, with his <hi>Fleet,</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily oppoſe the Power and Tyranny of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and engage their <hi>Navy</hi> or <hi>Armado;</hi> And after a Conjuction of his Forces with the States of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> he ſhall win a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult cruel Battel.</p>
                  <p>But God doth take out of this Life, the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Wife</hi> of the King, whence the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall be much troubled; whoſe Terror ſhall afterwards increaſe, when King <hi>Charles</hi> himſelf ſhall ſet himſelf againſt <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and prove a profeſt Adverſary unto him, and joyning his forces with the <hi>German</hi> Troops, and others of his Neighbours, ſhall pull down the <hi>Spaniſh Diadem.</hi> In thoſe days ſhall the <hi>Sweed</hi> be very ſucceſsful againſt the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, both by Sea and Land.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>Another Propheſie of the ſame Author, <hi>Vexillum. 238.</hi>
               </head>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BOhemia</hi> doth feel Tumults and Warlike noiſes, with a great falling away of her
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:65898:60"/>
People; and at that time the laſt <hi>Caeſar</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſhall put on the Noſe of the Elector of <hi>Saxony, Spaniſh</hi> deceitful and treacherous Spectacles; The Nature of which at laſt he knows, and by experience is taught, That theſe Spectacles of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> are vain encouragments, or flattering gloz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words, wicked and treacherous practiſes. If he goes on further to give credit to them, he ſhall caſt headlong himſelf, wife, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> into pernitious deſtruction, whence the People of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall rejoyce, and fall into a loud laughter.</p>
                  <p>But the Lord doth raiſe up an Elector, which ſhall throw down and root out the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Antichriſt</hi> in his Dominions, with all her Members and Abbetters: In this violent, precipitate, tumult raging, like the Sea in a tempeſt, and in the deſpair of the <hi>Roman Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> the Exiles of all the Kings and Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> the <hi>Bavarians, Bohemians, Burgundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the <hi>French,</hi> and the <hi>Portugals,</hi> ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to their former Eſtates and Liberties, and a Noble ſtout <hi>Bohemian</hi> Lord doth poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs and recover his Juriſdictions, by the meeting together of Armies, and their Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation; Theſe being expell'd ſhall ſeek their recovery, and their Heirs contend and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, that by the bounty of the new Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Germany,</hi> they may be ſet again in the place of their Anceſtors.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:65898:60"/>There ariſes a new Fortunate <hi>Bohemian Ziſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> who ſhall break the Heads of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and drive them out of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> who ſhall ſubdue to himſelf the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> &amp; all the Tract through <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and <hi>Pannonia,</hi> even as far as <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> it ſelf. Therefore, 'tis meet and requiſite, that a glittering preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Diadem be ſet upon the head of this <hi>Teu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonik Ziſca;</hi> who is the head of the ſtock, a great and valiant Warriour, that comes of the ſtock of <hi>Mars</hi> the Sixth. He ſhall rule victoriouſly, and do theſe famous things, happily finiſhing them with his other Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes and Captains.</p>
                  <p>After theſe Revolutions, a ſubtile exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Interpreter of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of St. <hi>John,</hi> may more eaſily be underſtood, and better decipher the ſame; The Nineties being paſt by little and little, between the Six Hundred and Six Years. Then ſhall be a moſt lively Explanation of thoſe things which <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> have Propheſied of the laſt Act of the Old Age of the World.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>A Prophecy recited by Mr. <hi>LILLY,</hi> in the Year <hi>1651.</hi> relating to the <hi>French</hi> Nation.</head>
               <q>
                  <p>A Certain Prince, as Religious as a <hi>Turk,</hi> ſhall overſpread that Peoples moſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:65898:61"/>
fruitful Territories, and Wars and Diſſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will be occaſioned by the unruly Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who by their Civil Diſſentions, ſhall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion the ruin of the <hi>French Monarchy.</hi> And if you will know near the time of this great Mutation, It ſhall be when a certain King, call'd <hi>Henry,</hi> is twice made a King, and a Duke of <hi>Florence</hi> turned <hi>Proteſtant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rex</hi> Franciae <hi>depelleter a ſuis finibus, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priis ſubditis, exercebit enim in eos Tyrannidem in Gentem, &amp; contra Eccleſiam Chriſti, inſtigatus ab Epiſcopis &amp; Pontificibus, qui proditorie aperta pecuma oppugnati, eum ſeducent &amp; tradent: Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe vero videbitur hoc facere ingratiam Affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Verum cum fuerit amotus &amp; falſus ſolus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquetur in auxilio, ab his in quibus erat confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Infine autem. Secundi Incurſus hoc fiet, ſic Pendet Clipeus in ſtipite.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>French</hi> King ſhall be driven out by his own People, For he will exerciſe very great Tyranny both againſt his Subjects, and the Church of Chriſt, being inſtigated or ſtirred up thereunto by the Biſhops and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts: who being bribed with mony, ſhall Trayterouſly ſeduce and betray him. This he ſhall ſeem to do in favour of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Allies, but when he ſhall be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and deceived, he ſhall be left all alone in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:65898:61"/>
baniſhment, abandon'd by thoſe that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fided in; This ſhall happen towards the end of the ſecond Incurſe, ſo the Shield hangs on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Fire-brand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Mahumetans <hi>very near that time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>hall poſſeſs</hi> Venice, <hi>and the Northern</hi> Eagle <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>luck down the Neſts of</hi> Monks <hi>and</hi> Fryars <hi>in</hi> Germany, <hi>and the</hi> Hollander <hi>be brought to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>entance, their Country at once drowned with Water, Blood, and Tears.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>A Prophecy of the Downfall of the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Empire,</hi> delivered by ſome of their own <hi>Diviners,</hi> in the <hi>Perſian</hi> Language, as followeth:</head>
               <q xml:lang="per">  
                  <p>PAtiſſahomoz ghelur: ciaferum memleketi alur, kenzul almai alur; Kapzeiler jediy ladeigh giaur keleci eſikmaſſe, on ikiyladegh ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aron. Beghlig eder, euſi japar, baghi dikers, bahuſai baghlur, oglikezi olur. Onichi ylden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſora Hriſtrianon keleci oſichar, ol Yurchi ghere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine tus chure.</p>
               </q>
               <p>The <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>  
                  <p>OUr <hi>Monarch</hi> ſhall come, He ſhall diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the Unbelieving Prince of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: He ſhall ſubdue the <hi>Red Apple,</hi> and make it yield to his Government. And if
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:65898:62"/>
happily the Chriſtian Sword prevail not unto the Seventh Year, he ſhall over-rule them unto the Twelfth Year: He ſhall build Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, plant Vineyards, and fortify his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens with Walls: He ſhall increaſe in iſſue: But after the aforeſaid Twelfth Year, the Sword of the Chriſtians ſhall approach, which ſhall put the <hi>Turks</hi> to flight, utterly van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing and deſtroying them.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Prophecy I find recited in a Treatiſe, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,</hi> A diſcourſive Problem concerning Prophecies, <hi>by</hi> John Harvey, <hi>Phyſitian of</hi> Kings-Lyn <hi>in</hi> Norfolk, <hi>(who appears by that work to have been a very Learned and Great-read Man) Publiſhed in the Year</hi> 1588. <hi>But when or by whom, the ſame was Originally Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the World, I have not been able to learn.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>
                  <hi>Truſwell</hi>'s Prophecy.</head>
               <p>THe following Prophecy is ancient, but who was the certain Author, I am no more able to aſſure, than what will be the certain event. However, let this ſuffice, That 'tis credibly reported to have been found in the Ruins of a Religious Houſe, at or near <hi>Lincoln,</hi> and given to one Mr. <hi>Truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> at that time Recorder of that City, from whom it now borrows the Name, and goes
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:65898:62"/>
under the Title of Mr. <hi>Truſwells Prophecy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Recorder of</hi> Lincoln. It was Writ in an Obſcure and Barbarous <hi>Latin,</hi> which does in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome meaſure ſhew the Antiquity of it, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat it was penn'd in thoſe Ages, when Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng was at ſo low an Ebb, that the High Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er-mark of it did not run above a ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>othiſh Latin;</hi> All beyond which was the <hi>Hercules</hi> Pillars, as they thought, with the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e plus ultra</hi> Inſcribed upon them, of <hi>Graecum <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t non poteſt legi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>The Prophecy.</label>
               </p>
               <q xml:lang="lat">LIlium manebit in meliori parte, &amp; movebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur contra <hi>Semen Leonis.</hi> Et ſtabit ex <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a parte inter ſpinas Regni ſui, cujus Regnum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Terra Lunae,</hi> per totum Orbem tremendum. Et veniet Filius hominis, ferens feras in <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>iis,</hi> cum multitudine Populi, tranſibit multas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>quas, &amp; veniet in <hi>Terram Leonis,</hi> auxilium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>arens a Beſtiis terrae ſuae. Veniet Aquila ex Oriente, aliis expanſis Radiis filii hominis. Et hoc anno Caſtra ſuper <hi>Thameſin</hi> peribunt, &amp; magnus erit Timor in toto Orbe, &amp; in quadam parte Terrae. Magna praelia erunt inter multos Reges. Et in illo die erit pugna cruenta in qua <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilium</hi> per det Coronam ſuam; de qua Coronabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur filius hominis. Et quarto anno multa erunt <hi>to Fide</hi> certamina; Caput mundi erit ad Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. Filius hominis &amp; Aquila elevabuntur:
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:65898:63"/>
Et tunc erit pax in Terris <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis. Et acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piet filius hominis mirabile ſignum. Et e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> magna frugum abundantia, &amp; ibi in terram Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cis.</q>
               <p>
                  <label>The <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </label>

                  <q>THe <hi>Lilly</hi> ſhall remain in the better par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and he ſhall be moved againſt the <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of the Lyon.</hi> And he ſhall ſtand on one pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> amongſt the Thorns of his Kingdom, who Kingdom is the <hi>Land of the Moon,</hi> which is be dreaded throughout the World. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> there ſhall come <hi>the Son of Man,</hi> bearing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Wild Beaſts in his Arms,</hi> with a Multitude People. He ſhall paſs many Waters, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall come to the Land of the <hi>Lyon,</hi> lookin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for help from the Beaſts of his own Countr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Then ſhall there come an <hi>Eagle</hi> out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Eaſt, and his Wings ſpread with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Beams of the <hi>Son of Man.</hi> And in that Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall be deſtroyed Caſtles upon the <hi>Tham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and there ſhall be great fear over all the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and eſpecially in one part of the Land. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall be great Battels amongſt many Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> In that day ſhall be the <hi>Bloody Field,</hi> in wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Lilly</hi> ſhall loſe his Crown, wherewith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Son of Man</hi> ſhall be Crown'd, and in the 14 Year, many Battles ſhall be fought for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Faith. The <hi>Head of the World</hi> ſhall brought down to the Duſt. And the <hi>Son
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:65898:63"/>
Man</hi> with the <hi>Eagle</hi> ſhall be exalted. And there ſhall be an Univerſal Peace over all the World. And the <hi>Son of Man</hi> ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a wonderful ſign. And there ſhall be great plenty of all Fruits of the Earth. And he ſhall go into the Land of the Croſs.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>The Prophecy of <hi>Malachy</hi> (a Popiſh Saint) declaring the Number, and ſome marks of all the <hi>Popes</hi> that ſhall be hereafter, together with the final deſtruction both of Popery, and the City of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis <hi>Malachy</hi> was Archbiſhop of <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of the <hi>Ciſtertian Order</hi> of <hi>Monks,</hi> a Contemporary with St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and very intimate with him about the year 1140: He pretending to the gift of Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, undertook by certain Hieroglyphical deſcriptions, to give an account of all and every the Popes that ſhould be from his time to the Worlds end: or at leaſt until the utter ſubverſion of the <hi>Papacy.</hi> All which I find both recited, and as far as then was accompliſht, explained, and by application found to be very true and ſignificant, in an <hi>Appendix</hi> to a Book, Intituled, <hi>Flores Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici,</hi> written by <hi>Johannes de Buſſieres,</hi> a French Jeſuit, abbout the year 1655.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:65898:64"/>To recite all the old Ones from the year 1143, would be both tedious and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, being ſo long paſt; thoſe that are curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous may find them in the Author juſt now cited: Only to give the Reader a Taſte, that he may the better apprehend the Humour of this Iriſh Pope-fortune-teller, I ſhall give you his <hi>Symbols,</hi> and their Explications, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove One hundred years paſt, and alſo all thoſe that are to come; and I will begin at the year 1550.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Propecy.</cell>
                        <cell>Popes Names.</cell>
                        <cell>The year of our Lord and Explanation.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>De Corona Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tana,</hi> the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and Crown,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Julius</hi> the Third.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>An.</hi> 1550. He was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before he came to the Popedom, <hi>John</hi> of the Mountain, and his Arms were Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Crowns of Laurel.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Frumentum Floc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidum,</hi> Bread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corn ſuddenly periſhing.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Marcellus</hi> Second.</cell>
                        <cell>1555. He had a blade of Wheat in his Arms, therefore ſaid to be ſuddenly periſhing, becauſe he continued a very little while in the Popedom.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>De Fide Petri,</hi> Of the Faith of <hi>Peter.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Paul</hi> the Fourth.</cell>
                        <cell>1555. His name was <hi>Peter de Carafe,</hi> which ſignifies as much as <hi>Peter,</hi> Of the dear Faith.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:65898:64"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Aeſculapii Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macum,</hi> The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine of the Phyſician.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth.</cell>
                        <cell>1560. He was before called <hi>Johannes Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus, John</hi> the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Angelus Nemoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> the Angel of the Wood.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Pius</hi> the Fifth.</cell>
                        <cell>1560. Call'd before <hi>Michael Boſchi,</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael Wood.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Medium Corpus pilarum,</hi> a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle body of Balls.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gregory</hi> the Thirteenth</cell>
                        <cell>1572. His Arms, the middle of a Dragon, and was made Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal by <hi>Pius</hi> the 4th, who had the Balls in his Arms.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Axis in Medieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſigni,</hi> the Axle-tree in the midſt of a Sign.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fifth.</cell>
                        <cell>1583. His Arms an Axle-tree in the midſt of <hi>Leo.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>De Rore Coeli,</hi> from Heavens Dew.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Seventh.</cell>
                        <cell>1590. He was Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop in <hi>Calabria,</hi> where Manna is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ex Antiquitate <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbis,</hi> from a City of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fourteen.</cell>
                        <cell>1590. Of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Pia Civitas in Bello,</hi> a City pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in War.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Innocent</hi> the Ninth.</cell>
                        <cell>1590. Of <hi>Bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:65898:65"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Crux Romulea,</hi> the Roman Croſs.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Clement</hi> the Eighth.</cell>
                        <cell>1592. His Arms a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple oblique Papal Croſs.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoſus vir,</hi> A man gone as ſoon as a Wave.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Leo</hi> the Eleventh.</cell>
                        <cell>1605. He continued but Four and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty days.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gens perverſa,</hi> a perverſe people.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth.</cell>
                        <cell>1605. In his days the <hi>Bobemians</hi> roſe againſt the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> whom our Author will have to be the perverſe Nation; but why not rather the <hi>Venetians,</hi> with whom this Pope had great Broils.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>In tribulatione Pacis,</hi> in the work of Peace.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fifth.</cell>
                        <cell>1621. As ſoon as he was made Cardinal he was ſent by <hi>Paul</hi> 5th. Legate to <hi>Sav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>y,</hi> &amp; concluded a peace between the Duke and the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and ſoon after was choſen Pope.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Lilium a Roſa,</hi> the Lilly and Roſe.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the Eighth.</cell>
                        <cell>1623. <hi>A Florentine,</hi> which City is ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from <hi>Flowers,</hi> and has a Roſe in is Arms.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Jucunditas Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> the joy of the Croſs.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Innocent</hi> the Tenth.</cell>
                        <cell>1644.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Montium Cuſtos,</hi> the Keeper of the Mountains.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Alexander</hi> the 7th.</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:65898:65"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Sidus Olorum,</hi> the Conſtellation of Swans.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Clement</hi> the 9th.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Roſpiglioſi,</hi> he had the Star and Swan in his Arms.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>De Flumine mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> of the great River.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Clement</hi> the 10th.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Altieri,</hi> born at the time of a great Inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the River <hi>Tyber.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bellua inſatiabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> an inſatiable Beaſt.</cell>
                        <cell>Innocent 11th.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Odiſchalchi</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Pope, called an inſatiable Beaſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his great covetouſneſs.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>The <hi>Symbols</hi> or <hi>Hieroglyphicks</hi> of all the Popes in order that ſhall be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>POenitentia glorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa,</hi> A glorious Penitent.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Raſtrum in Porta,</hi> A rake in the Gate.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Flores circumdati,</hi> Flowers encompaſſing</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>De bona Religione,</hi> Of a good Religion. [I wiſh we might ſee ſuch a Pope once!]</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Miles in Bello,</hi> A Souldier in War.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cobumna excelſa,</hi> A lofty Pillar.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Animal rurale,</hi> A rural Animal.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Roſa <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbriae,</hi> A Roſe of <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbria.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:65898:66"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Viſus velox,</hi> A quick ſight.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peregrinus Apoſtolicus,</hi> An Apoſtolical Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grim.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aquila rapax,</hi> A ravenous Eagle.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Canis &amp; Coluber,</hi> A Dog and a Snake.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vir Religioſus,</hi> A Religious man.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>De Balneis Hetruria,</hi> From the Baths of <hi>Tuſcany.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Crux de Cruce,</hi> Croſs of Croſs.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lumen de Coelo,</hi> A light from Heaven.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ignis ardens,</hi> A flaming fire.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Religio depopulata,</hi> Religion laid waſte.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fides intrepida,</hi> Faith fearleſs.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Paſtor Angelicus,</hi> An Angelick Paſtor.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Paſtor &amp; Nauta,</hi> Both Shepherd and Sailer.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Flos florum,</hi> The Flower of Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>De mediteate Lunae,</hi> Half the Moon.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>De labore Solis,</hi> The labour of the <hi>Sun,</hi> or an eclipſe.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gloria Olivae,</hi> The Glory of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>After which our Iriſh Prophet concludes with this ſad 

<q xml:lang="lat">  O hone! hone! —In perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutione extrema Sacrae Romanae Eccleſiae ſedebit Petrus Romanus, qui paſcet Oves in multis Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulationibus quibus tranſactis Civitas Sep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>icollis diruetur, &amp; judex tremendus judicabit popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:65898:66"/>
               <p>In Engliſh thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>In the laſt Perſecution of the Holy <hi>Roman Church,</hi> one <hi>Peter</hi> a Roman ſhall poſſeſs the Chair, and feed the Sheep in many Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; which being accompliſhed, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-hill'd City ſhall be deſtroyed, and the dreadful Judge ſhall call the people to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</q>
Hitherto the words tranſlated out of the before-mentioned Jeſuite's <hi>Floſculi Hiſtorici.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There being according to this man's reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning, Twenty ſix of their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nholineſſes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, if we ſhall allow (according to our u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Eſtimate of a man's life) ſeven years to each, it will amount to 182 years, that is, to the year of our Lord 1865, before the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal deſtruction of the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and that bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy City ſhall be compleated: But the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the faithful, and the Cries of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs from under the Altar, may, 'tis like, ſooner draw down and accelerate the juſt Judgments threatned to this <hi>Babylon</hi> and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>Sodom; Quod faxit Deus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>A very ancient Prophecy of <hi>Gildas</hi> the <hi>Scot,</hi> recited by Archbiſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> in his Book, Intituled, <hi>De Britanicarum Eccleſiarum Primoraiis, Page</hi> 680.</head>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>FAta ducis celebris ſuper omnia Scotia flebit,</l>
                  <l>Qui loca Septa Salo junget ubique ſibi.</l>
                  <l>Principe magnifico Tellus viduata vacabit</l>
                  <l>Annis bis Ternis, menſibus atque novem.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:65898:67"/>Antiquos Reges, juſtos, fortes, Locupletes</l>
                  <l>Largos, Famoſos, Scotia maeſta luget;</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Merlinus ait, poſt Reges victorioſus</l>
                  <l>Regis more carens Regia Sceptra Reget.</l>
                  <l>Vae canet Albaniae tantis praeſaga Ruims</l>
                  <l>Totaque Gens propria fraude perempta jacet,</l>
                  <l>Quod reſpirabit, poſt funus Regis avari</l>
                  <l>Verſibus antiquis priſca ſibylla canit.</l>
                  <l>Candidus Albanus Patriotis cauſa Ruinae</l>
                  <l>Traditione ſua Scotica Regna teret;</l>
                  <l>Rex borealis enim numeroſa Claſſe potitus</l>
                  <l>Affliget Scotos enſe, furore, fame.</l>
                  <l>Extera gens tandem Sociorum fraude peribit</l>
                  <l>In bello Princeps Noricus enſe cadet.</l>
                  <l>Gallica quem gignet, qui Gazis Regna replebit,</l>
                  <l>O dolor! O Gemitus! Fratris ab enſe cadet.</l>
                  <l>Triſtia ceſſabunt, quae proſpera fine ſequuntur</l>
                  <l>Pacis &amp; adveniat Tempore grata quies</l>
                  <l>Hiſtoriae veteris <hi>Gildas</hi> luculentus Amator</l>
                  <l>Haec retulit parvo Carmine, plura notans.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Which as near the <hi>Senſe</hi> as I can, to make i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Verſe,</hi> I thus Engliſh; Thoſe that can Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late it more exactly, let them.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SCotland</hi> 'bove all ſhall her brave Chief bemoan,</l>
                  <l>Who all the <hi>Sea-girt</hi> places Rules alone;</l>
                  <l>The Widdowed Land of bounteous Prince bereſt,</l>
                  <l>Shall Twice Three Years, and Nine long Months be left.</l>
                  <l>Sad <hi>Scotland</hi> mourns her Old Juſt valiant Kings,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Merlin</hi> ſays, after them up their Springs</l>
                  <l>One that ſhall not in Kingly manner ſway</l>
                  <l>The Royal Scepter, yet makes them obey.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:65898:67"/>To <hi>Albany</hi> preſaging Ruin flows,</l>
                  <l>By their own fraud undone, more than their Foes.</l>
                  <l>Yet Old <hi>Sybil</hi> in Ancient Rhimes has told</l>
                  <l>She ſhall revive, when one that dotes on Gold</l>
                  <l>Is laid to reſt. The <hi>White Albanion</hi> then</l>
                  <l>By Treachery, undoes his Countrymen:</l>
                  <l>A Northern Prince with numerous Ships ſhall vex</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Scot;</hi> whom Fury, Sword, and Death perplex.</l>
                  <l>The Forraigner by fraud of his Allies</l>
                  <l>Is loſt, and in diſaſtrous Battle Dies.</l>
                  <l>Th' <hi>French-Womans</hi> Bearn, who ſhall his Kingdoms fill</l>
                  <l>With Wealth; Alas! A Brother's Sword ſhall kill.</l>
                  <l>Soon after, ſorrows ceaſe, and joys appear,</l>
                  <l>And Welcome Peace ſalutes our Hemiſphere,</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Gildas</hi> in ſtory well-read foreſhows,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Verſe, thouth brief, much matter may diſcloſe.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>The words of Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> (Printed with Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence) in his <hi>Almanack,</hi> 1677.</head>
               <q>
                  <p>AS to the time of Manifeſtation when theſe ſo wonderful Mutations or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions ſhall be effected or viſibly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or put into Action; We ſay, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in part ſome breakings out there are in <hi>eſſe</hi> at preſent, yet the moſt violent Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or dreadful Concerments, ſhall not have full Manifeſtation, or perfect appearance, until Three times Ten Years added to 1669. do come, which will be 1699.— Weighty matters require many Years for their performances, yet in the mean time the powerful Configurations of the Superior Planets, the remaining Influences of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, or Comets in 1664, 1665. and alſo of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:65898:68"/>
that 1673. have in ſome meaſure begun thoſe Effects which will in convenient time be more apparent, long before the Year 1699.</p>
                  <p>In the Year 1682. and Month of <hi>October, (Viz.)</hi> the Twentieth Day, there will be a Conjunction of the two Superior Planets, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in the Twentieth degree of that Regal Sign <hi>Leo,</hi> which is the Terms of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and wherein he and the Sun have their <hi>Triplicity.</hi> It will be the Fifth time of their meeting in the Fiery <hi>Triplicity,</hi> ſince their Conjunction in 1603. at what time they changed one <hi>Triplicity,</hi> and entred into another: which uſually (if we may credit Antiquity, Experience, or Hiſtory,) hath not happened without conſiderable Revolutions and Changes in the World; <hi>(Viz.)</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Nature and Sign of the Planet moſt Eſſentially fortified.—We have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, That thoſe Conjunctions which have happened in the Year 1603. and ſince ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in the Fiety <hi>Trygon,</hi> have not been accompanyed with Propitious Succeſſes unto <hi>England,</hi> or the City of <hi>London.</hi> At the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of thoſe Planets into the Fiery <hi>Trygon,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> dyed. In 1603. a great Plague was in <hi>London,</hi> and in the Year 1623. the Second Conjunction of the Superior Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets fell in the Seventh Degree of <hi>Leo.</hi> Not long after King <hi>James</hi> (a Peaceable and Wiſe Prince) dyed; Again, in the Year 1625. at
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:65898:68"/>
leaſt 50000 Perſons dyed of the Plague in <hi>London.</hi> In ſhort time after follows the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate buſineſs or attempt of the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Rhee</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the Murther of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> &amp;c. and during all that time a general murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and repining of the Common People, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially amongſt thoſe of different Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which gave encouragment to and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of our late unhappy Troubles and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine Wars.</p>
                  <p>In the Year 1642/3;. the Third Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> was celebrated in Twenty Six Degrees of <hi>Piſces;</hi> but the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects moſt concerned thoſe People ſubject to the Sign <hi>Aries.</hi> Upon this Conjunction our late unhappy Calamities began, which more or leſs continued until the Year 1652. In that Inteſtine and Bloody War, many Thouſand Perſons of all Degrees and Qualities miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſuffered, and the City of <hi>London</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in her Trade and Commerce. What is moſt remarkable after the Year 1663; was, That in 1665, <hi>(Viz.)</hi> the greateſt Plague that ever happened in <hi>London,</hi> wherein 'tis credibly reported, that near One Hundred Thouſand People periſhed. And beſides, in the Year 1666. that terrible and never to be forgotten Fire, which deſtroyed the greateſt part of that Famous and Flouriſhing City: and theſe Calamities followed the Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in the Sign <hi>Sagitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi>
                     <pb n="116" facs="tcp:65898:69"/>
of the Fiery <hi>Trygon, Anno.</hi> 1663.—But what manner of accidents ſhall precede or follow this next Conjunction of the Superiors in the Kingly Sign <hi>Leo, Anno</hi> 1682. which will be One Hundred Years and Ten, after the <hi>Mock-ſtar</hi> of 1572. and Seventy Nine Years after the great Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> 1603. and Seventeen Years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the appearance of the Comet in 1665, whoſe tail extended Fiery and large towards the Eaſt part of Heaven, The Effects where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we Judge are not yet in being, but will in part be put forward in or about the Year 1682. or ſomething later: with an heavy venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance or judgment on thoſe People and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Providence ſhall diſpoſe the Effects to fall upon; by Wars, Famine, Death of Cattle, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Mortalities, barrenneſs of the Earth, and cruel deſtruction of Mankind.—It por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends great Rents and Schiſms amongſt the Religious Odrers of Monks, Fryars, Jeſuits, as alſo amongſt thoſe of different Judgments, call them by what Name you pleaſe; And this Judgment is the more aggravated, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard theſe Two Superior Planets, <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> do alſo meet again in the Sign <hi>Leo,</hi> in <hi>May</hi> 1683. (as appears by Calculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and alſo by the Ephemerides of <hi>Argol.</hi>) And hence I conclude this Conjunction to be the <hi>Prodromus</hi> of every Prodigious Effects, —which we may not live to ſee tranſacted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:65898:69"/>There will be ſome preceding differences (perhaps <hi>Verbal</hi>) which will begin to break forth at firſt clandeſtinely before thoſe great Deluges of Affairs are tranſacted. For we find, that upon the Fifth Day of <hi>September,</hi> 1682. there will firſt be a Conjunction of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and upon the Twelfth Day of the ſame Month in the aforeſaid Year, there will be another Conjunction of <hi>Tory Mars</hi> with <hi>Saturn,</hi> in the Seventeenth Degree of the ſame Sign; and again, in <hi>December</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, there happens a Conjunction of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> alſo, in or near Twenty De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees thereof, and both ſwift motion. Then matters, Treaſons, Conſultations, Treachery of Subjects againſt their Superiors, are Plotting, Contriving, or Agitating, ſome Years before this Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> is Celebrated.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe pretending to Religion, or ſuch as are Famous for Schiſms, Haereſies, or of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Judgments from the Profeſſion of that Religion which is eſtabliſht by Authority, will for ſome Years grumble and repine for Reſtriction of their Conſciences (as the will term it) and the nearer the time of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction it ſelf, or a little after, we fear greater diſturbances of thoſe Nations, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they live under, diſquieting their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours: and this for Conſcience-ſake, as they pretend. But in ſome Nations, Breach of the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:65898:70"/>
Peoples juſt Priviledges, Ancient Cuſtoms and former enjoy'd Rights, will animate the Generality to a ſtrong and ſturdy Rebellion and countenance that Tranſlation of <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chy,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Trithemius.</hi>—Certainly you Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> as alſo the <hi>Roman Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> or <hi>Conclave</hi> of <hi>Cardinals</hi> of the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> will all of you find great and moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous diſtempers in your Governments, near the time limited: So will many People and Nations ſubject to the Fiery <hi>Triplicity,</hi> and this Evil will be the more aggravated to thoſe Kingdoms or Governments ſubject to the Signs <hi>Taurus, Leo, Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Aquary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Many believe the laſt Age of the World is at hand, we verily conjecture that a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and vexatious time is approaching upon moſt Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> wherein thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Religion, whether Papiſts or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, will ſhew little mercy or compaſſion to thoſe perſons whoſe unhappineſs it will be to fall under their ſubjection.—The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adunation of ſo many Planets in the Sign <hi>Leo,</hi> in the Year 1682. gives very rational grounds to predict the appearance of another Comet, very ſtrange Apparitions in the Air, or ſome Prodigious Meteors, either prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that Conjunction, or ſubſequent in a ſhort time after: And we alſo are fearful that ſome more than ordinary Fire or Fires may afflict or do conſiderable damage to many
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:65898:70"/>
Cities of <hi>Europe;</hi> God keep this Judgment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Bleſs her Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants with much Health and Proſperity, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eliver her from another Plague or Peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al diſtemper in thoſe Years.</p>
               </q>
               <p>Thus <hi>Lilly</hi> divers Years ſince, wherein his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rediction of a Comet in 82. which exactly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>appened in <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, being viſible both morning and evening for many Nights; his mentioning the Word <hi>Tory,</hi> which when he wrote was not in uſe, though ſince the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of many Animoſities, his Menaces of more miſchief by Fire, ſadly felt by the poor Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Wapping</hi> near <hi>London,</hi> on the Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth of <hi>November,</hi> this preſent Year 1682. whereby about 1000 houſes were conſumed, are very remarkable, and how far the reſt may anſwer Truth, time may ſhew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prophecy">
               <head>A Prophecy found in the Library of <hi>Saliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> of <hi>Heidelburg</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> almoſt 200 years ſince.</head>
               <q>THere ſhall a King ariſe out of the Nation of the moſt Illuſtrious <hi>Lilly,</hi> having a long Forehead, high Brows, great Eyes, and an Eagles Noſe; He ſhall gather a great Army, and deſtroy all the Tyrants of his Kingdom, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay all that fly into Mountains and Caves from his Face; for Righteouſneſs ſhall be joyned unto him, as the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom unto the Bride. With them he ſhall wage War e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto the Fortieth year, bringing into ſubjection the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>landers, Spaniards and Italians; <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Florence</hi> he ſhall deſtroy and burn with fire, ſo as Salt may be ſowed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n that Land. The greateſt Clergy-men who have Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Peter</hi>'s Seat, he ſhall put to death, and in the ſame year obtain a double Crown. At laſt, going over-Sea with A great Army, he ſhall enter <hi>Greece,</hi> and be named <hi>King of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:65898:71"/>
the Greeks.</hi> The Turks and Barbarians he ſhall ſubdue making an Edict, <hi>That every one ſhall die the Death, that worſhippeth not the crucified One, and none ſhall be found able to reſiſt him, becauſe an Holy Arm from the Lord ſhall alway<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be with him, and he ſhall be with him, and he ſhall poſſeſs the Dominions of the Earth.</hi> Theſe things being done, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be called, <hi>The Reſt of the Holy Chriſtians.</hi>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>The <hi>Apocalyptical Interpreters</hi> adventuring to ſail in the vaſt Ocean of Futurity, have moſt-timeS ſhip-wrackt their judgment and credit do the Rocks of Preſumption; ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I ſhall preſume here to add the words of that Reverend French Divine <hi>Peter du Moulin,</hi> in his Book Intituled, <hi>The Accompliſhment of Prophecies,</hi> (Tranſlated into Engliſh, <hi>Anno</hi> 1613 <hi>Page</hi> 411. as follows:</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>As for the time of three days and an half, during which the Bodies of the faithful Witneſſes ſhall be caſt out through all the Quarters of the Roman Church: It is manifeſt, that S.</hi> John <hi>doth hereby ſhew us how long the Perſecution of the Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Roman Hierarchy, muſt continue. For to know how long this time ſhall endure, and to how much the Three Days and an half will amount unto; we are to note, that Three Days and an half, make half a Week, which gives us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the Holy Ghoſt here under the name of a Week, doth comprehend the whole time of the Beaſt's Reign, and doth advertiſe us, that the Perſecution ſhall laſt half the time of this Reign. Since therefore he ſhall Reign</hi> 1260 <hi>years (as we have ſhewed before) it followeth that the Roman Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy ſhall perſecute the Faithful</hi> 630 <hi>years. Now I do not find, that the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>did begin to perſecute and is uſe cruelty in general againſt all that did withſtand her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine till the time of</hi> Berengarius <hi>whom Pope</hi> Nicholas <hi>the Second compelled to Recant by force, in the year</hi> 1059; <hi>and ever ſince the Popes have perſecuted ſuch as have maintained the ſame Doctrine. If then you add the</hi> 630 <hi>years to</hi> 1059 <hi>years, you ſhall find that the perſecution of the Church under the Pope, ſhall have an end in the year of our Lord</hi> 1689. <hi>This Term once expired, the Truth that was oppreſſed ſhall lift up her head afreſh, and the faithful Witneſſes ſhall be ſeen to ſtand up again, who ſhall aſtoniſh the Church of</hi> Rome.</q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:65898:71"/>The Prediction of the moſt Learned and pious Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> is very remarkable, as it was printed above a years ago with Licence, and the Truth of the matter of Fact therein delivered, never that I know of denied, out confirmed by many, which in ſhort was thus.—<hi>That the year before this holy Primate died (who was buried in the</hi> Abbey <hi>at</hi> Weſtminiſter 17 <hi>of</hi> April, 1656. <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> Cromwel <hi>allowing</hi> 200 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                  <hi>towards his Funeral, ſo great his Worth, that it even charmed that Tyrant, otherwiſe far from being a Friend to any of his Profe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſon:) An intimate Friend of the Archbiſhop's asking him (amongſt other diſcourſe) what his preſent Apprehenſions were concerning a very great Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ution which ſhould fall upon the Church of God in theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of</hi> England, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>(of which he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eard him ſpeak with great confidence many years before, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e were in the higheſt and fulleſt ſtate of outward peace and ſettlement) and whether he did believe thoſe ſad Times to be paſt, or that they were yet to come?</hi> —He anſwered,—<hi>That they were yet to come, and that he did as confidently expect it as ever he had done.</hi> Adding, <hi>That this ſad Perſecution would fall upon all the Proteſtant Churches of</hi> Europe. His Friend arguing, that he hoped the Affliction might now be over, and be intended of our late calamitous <hi>Civil Wars.</hi> The reverend Prelate turning towards him, and fixing his Eyes upon him with that ſerious and ſevere Look which he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually had when he ſpake God's Word, and not his own, and when the power of God ſeemed to be upon him, and to conſtrain him to ſpeak, ſaid thus: <hi>Fool not your ſelf with ſuch hopes, for I tell you, all you have yet ſeen, hath been but the beginning of ſorrows to what is yet to come upon the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches of Chriſt, who will ere long fall under a ſharper Perſecution than ever yet has been upon them; and therefore</hi> (ſaid he to him) <hi>Look you be not found in the Outward Court, but a Worſhipper in the Trmple before the Altar, for Chriſt will meaſure all thoſe that profeſs his Name, and call themſelves his People; and the Outward Worſhippers he will leave out, to be trodden down by the Gentiles. The outward Court</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is the formal Chriſtian, whoſe Religion lies in performing the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide duties of Chriſtianity, without having an inward Life and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:65898:72"/>
Power of Faith and Love, uniting them to Chriſt, and theſe God will leave to be trodden down, and ſwept away by the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles: But the Worſhippers within the Temple, and before the Altar, are thoſe who do indeed worſhip God to Spirit and Truth, whoſe Souls are made his Temples, and he is honoured and adored in the moſt inward thoughts of their hearts, and they ſacrifice their Luſts and vile Affections, yea, and their own Wills to him; and theſe God will hide in the hollow of his Hand, and under the ſhadow of his Wings; and this ſhall be one great difference between this laſt, and all the other prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Perſecutions; For in the former, the moſt eminent and ſpiritual Miniſters and Chriſtians did generally ſuffer moſt, and were most violently fallen upon, but in this laſt Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, theſe ſhall be preſerved by God as a Seed to partake of that Glory which ſhall immediately follow and come upon the Church, as ſoon as ever this ſtorm ſhall be over; for as it ſhall be the ſharpeſt, ſo it ſhall be the ſhorteſt Perſecution of them all; and ſhall only take away the groſs Hypocrites and formal Profeſſors, but the true Spiritual Believers ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved till the Calamity be over-paſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Friend then asked him, By what means or Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments this great Tryal ſhould be brought on. He anſwered, By the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> His Friend replyed, That it ſeemed very improbable they ſhould be able to do it, ſince they were now little countenanced, and but few in theſe Nations, and that the hearts of the People were more ſet againſt them than ever ſince the Reformation. He anſwered again, 
<q rend="margQuotes">That it would be by the hands of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and in the way of a ſuddain Maſſacre, and that the then Pope ſhould be the chief Inſtrument of it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>He alſo added, 
<q rend="margQuotes">That the <hi>Papiſts</hi> were in his Opinion the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. to whom the Outward Court ſhould be left, that they might tread it under foot; they having received the <hi>Gentiles</hi> worſhip in their ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Images, and Saints departed, and in taking to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves many Mediators: And this (ſaid he) the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are now deſigning among themſelves, and therefore be ſure you be ready.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:65898:72"/>This gracious man repeated the ſame things in Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance to his only daughter the Lady <hi>Tyrril,</hi> and that with many tears, and much about the ſame time.</p>
               <p>We the rather have mention'd this, becauſe we find: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of our moſt Reverend Divines have foretold or intimated a Return of Popery—As appears by the Book Intituled <hi>Fair warning,</hi> the Second part, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht with the Licenſe of Dr. <hi>Stradling,</hi> wherein are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited Twenty Prophecies by Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> Arch-Biſhop <hi>Bancroft,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> and others to the ſame purpoſe,</p>
               <p>But if God in Judgment for our Sins ſhould ſuffer it ſo to be, yet 'Tis certain, the Joy of the Wicked ſhall be but for a moment, for We have a moſt ſure word of Prophecy, that in <hi>due time Rome</hi> ſhall final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall, And the Kings of the Earth ſhall hate the Whore, and make her deſolate and naked, and burn her with Fire, Rev. 17.16.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> tottering long, laden with Errors ſtore,</l>
                  <l>At laſt ſhall fall, and Head the World no more.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
